<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A new-years-gift for Doctor Witty, or, The dissector anatomized which is a reply to the discourse intituled, An answer to all that Doctor Tonstall has writ, or shall hereafter write, against Scarbrough spaw.</title>
            <author>Tonstall, George, b. 1616 or 17.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 178 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 100 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62931</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1888</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21567</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12297197</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12297197</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59064</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62931)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59064)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 927:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A new-years-gift for Doctor Witty, or, The dissector anatomized which is a reply to the discourse intituled, An answer to all that Doctor Tonstall has writ, or shall hereafter write, against Scarbrough spaw.</title>
                  <author>Tonstall, George, b. 1616 or 17.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30], 162, [6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.M. for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to George Tonstall. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hydrotherapy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59064:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59064:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A NEW-YEARS-GIFT FOR Doctor <hi>WITTY;</hi> OR THE DISSECTOR ANATOMIZED: Which is a reply to the Diſcourſe Intituled, <hi>An Anſwer to all that Doctor</hi> TONSTALL <hi>has writ, or ſhall hereafter Write, againſt</hi> SCARBROUGH <hi>Spaw.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Aeger non quaerit Medicum Eloquentem ſed ſanantem.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Seneca.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. M.</hi> for the Author. MDCLXXII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:59064:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59064:2"/>
            <head>TO THE <hi>ROYAL SOCIETY.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF there were no Judges to determine Controverſies, Diſputes would be endleſs. <hi>Dr. Witty</hi> having ſaid all he can, in anſwer to my Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions againſt <hi>Scarbrough Spaw,</hi> He makes his <hi>ultimate</hi> and <hi>higheſt</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to the <hi>Right Honourable Lords,</hi> to whom he Dedicates his Book, ſaying, <hi>What fitter Judges of this Controverſie, can be found out, than their Lordſhips.</hi> And in the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his Preface, he ſeems to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the difference betwixt him and
<pb facs="tcp:59064:3"/>me, to the <hi>major Vote</hi> of the <hi>Right Honourable,</hi> and <hi>Right Worſhipful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus he prefers <hi>Alexander</hi> for a more Competent Judge of <hi>A Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophical queſtion</hi> before <hi>Ariſtotle;</hi> as if <hi>Titles</hi> of Honour were infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible <hi>Amulets</hi> and <hi>Charms</hi> againſt <hi>miſtakes;</hi> and that none of thoſe were to be impoſed upon, by the common Tricks and Juggles of one, who, with confidence, would perſwade them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Water (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the great proportion of Sand and Clay in it) will <hi>leave none</hi> of this in our Bodies, becauſe he has let them ſee (Pag. 42.) <hi>That it will paſs, when newly taken out of the Fountain, through the filter, leaving nothing behind:</hi> or,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That the Water cannot poſſibly occaſion Obſtructions, becauſe it moves to ſtool,</hi> (p. 108.)</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That it cannot breed Stones in
<pb facs="tcp:59064:3"/>the Kidneys, becauſe it provokes to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine,</hi> (p. 37.)</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That it muſt be good to prevent and cure the Gout, becauſe it purgeth,</hi> (p. 109.)</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>That it is a moſt innocent Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and good for all, becauſe ſome who are ſtrong in their diſtributive faculty, have quitted themſelves from the Sandy faeces, without taking harm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So confident he is in the ſtrength of theſe reaſonings, that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes (<hi>p.</hi> 126) <hi>Nor do I think that there is a more innocent Water in the world of this kind, in the very par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars he hath charged it withal.</hi> Self-opinion is a thing ſo natural to all men, that it may be found in thoſe that ſay, they know not what, and that do like him, <hi>Magno conatu nugas agere;</hi> but his <hi>ipſe dixit,</hi> can neither ſatisfie <hi>you,</hi> nor ſilence <hi>me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing therefore you have avow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:59064:4"/>to examine all opinions in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Philoſophy, by the teſt of Experiment (a foundation for truth that will never fail) and that I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be tryed thereby, <hi>I make mine appeal to you;</hi> were it a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>ſmall</hi> concernment, not worth your cognizance, I ſhould not be ſo rude, as to beg, that ſentence may be pronounced by you; according to the <hi>merit</hi> of the Cauſe, ſo let your judgments be. I have evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced the <hi>Quiddity</hi> of petrifying waters, agreeable to <hi>Kirchers</hi> defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, by experimenting the <hi>drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Well at Knaisbrough,</hi> which <hi>Dr. Witty</hi> ſays, <hi>is the moſt famous petrifying water, by far, of any that this Kingdom doth afford,</hi> (p. 54.) Of that Water, before it came to the Rock, I diſtilled a quart, and there was half a dram of pure Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Salt remaining. <hi>The Cattle he ſays drinks of it, neither is there any
<pb facs="tcp:59064:4"/>Symboles of a petrifying property in it.</hi> 'Tis very true, for it has been tryed by ſeveral; but as ſoon as it runs into the Rock, and comes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilling forth on the other ſide, then it petrifies, becauſe the Nitrous Water has now diſſolved ſtone, which it had not done before; I diſtilled a quart of this Water alſo, and it gave, as I ſaid, a dram want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ten Grains, of Stone Powder and Nitre.</p>
            <p>Here let it be obſerved, that the ſureſt way to diſcover whether a Water be petrifying or no, is to diſtil, or boil it in a double Veſſel, to ſee what Sediment remains, or is caſt down to the bottom; if it be Sand (which is ſtone powder) that Water is certainly petrifying. As for trying it by putting moſs or ſticks in the Water, to ſee if it will lay a cruſt of ſtone upon them, <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leat argumentum affirmativè;</hi> but it
<pb facs="tcp:59064:5"/>is a fallacious Experiment, <hi>negative,</hi> to deny it to be a petrifying Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in caſe it do not incruſtate.</p>
            <p>Becauſe there are other circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances requiſite, beſides a petri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying property in the Water, to perform this incruſtation, the main requiſite (I judge) is, that the Experiment be made, whilſt the Water flows <hi>immediately</hi> out of the Rock, and is in its act of <hi>Corroſion.</hi> I dare affirm, that all the tryals had by things petrifyed, were thus ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; whereas if the ſame things were left in the <hi>Currant</hi> of theſe petrifying Waters, <hi>after</hi> the act of <hi>Corroſion</hi> were fully <hi>compleated</hi> (I ſuppoſe a mile or two diſtant from the Rock) from whence the Water took its petrifying proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) they would not then be Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted over.</p>
            <p>'Tis more than probable, that this is the caſe of <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb facs="tcp:59064:5"/>wherefore it doth not lay a Cruſt of ſtone upon the things put in it, notwithſtanding it be a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifying Water. For it runs out of the South, and in a direct line Southward, a mile or two diſtant beyond the great Mountains, there is an <hi>Hydrophilacia,</hi> a ſtately Lake abounding with Fiſh; here is the Spring-head of <hi>Scarbrough Spaw,</hi> it paſſing forthwith through the Roots of thoſe Stony Hills, <hi>firſt,</hi> Diſſolves the <hi>ſtone,</hi> and hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed fully the <hi>act</hi> of <hi>Corroſion</hi> on it, before it come to the <hi>Cliff.</hi> This being done, it then Corrodes <hi>Allom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone</hi> and in this <hi>ſecond</hi> act of <hi>Corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> the Spaw appears at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of the <hi>Cliff,</hi> after the <hi>Corroſion</hi> is compleated; which happens in a day or two; it ſettles to the bottom the Glebe of Allom. See for this, what I ſay to (<hi>p.</hi> 102.) the Tenth Propoſition. A ſecond requiſite for
<pb facs="tcp:59064:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>incruſtation is, that the <hi>Saline</hi> water, which has newly diſſolved <hi>ſtone,</hi> do <hi>penetrate</hi> through the <hi>pores</hi> of what is laid in it, that thereby it may leave a cruſt of Stone upon it; that this is neceſſary alſo, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by this. The more porous any thing is, that is put into all pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifying waters the ſooner, and more perfectly is it incruſtated. There is a Water, a mile diſtant from the dropping Well, that will petrifie neither Leaf nor Stick, or other thing, ſave Moſs only; and that is grown ſo hard upon the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of that Water, that one may go over it, as on a Bridge.</p>
            <p>The cauſe, <hi>ſine qua non,</hi> of all petrifying Waters is, that the <hi>Saline Water</hi> paſſeth through the Stone, whilſt it is in <hi>Embryone,</hi> and therefore diſſolves it. If it were not ſo then, all Saline Waters (which muſt be ſuppoſed to paſs
<pb facs="tcp:59064:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>through ſtone, before it appear above ground) would be petrify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but we know the contrary; for the <hi>Sulphurous Salt</hi> Well at <hi>Knaiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough,</hi> and the Allom Well at <hi>Malton,</hi> has not a grain of ſtone powder in them.</p>
            <p>'Tis a memorable thing, which the <hi>Lord Thomas Fairfax</hi> told to me; he cut away an high Rock near his houſe, at <hi>Denton,</hi> above the ground; and a good way with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Earth,
'twas very hard, but the nearer they came to the root of the Stone (his <hi>Lordſhips</hi> own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion) the ſofter the Rock was, even till at laſt it was nothing but Sand, that had not contracted the firmneſs of a Stone. Removing the heap of Sand, they came at laſt to Water and Clay, the mother of all that great Rock.</p>
            <p>That Stone which is ſubject to Corruption, may alſo be generated.
<pb facs="tcp:59064:7"/>I need not waſte time to prove be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, 'tis viſibly to be obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that Stone has its ſeed, by look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Rock of the <hi>Dropping Well,</hi> where the Water runs out of the ſame Chinks, where it has done from the beginning, and will do to the worlds end. Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Water (as <hi>Dr. Witty</hi> has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed it) running into the River <hi>Nidd</hi> (a little way diſtant from it) has Corroded ſo much Stone, <hi>that it has made a Rock that ſtretches ſome yards into the River;</hi> which ſhews, that the Nitrous Water would have conſumed the Rock, which it continually Corrodes, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Nature do ſupply it by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued act of Generation.</p>
            <p>Not to give you any further trouble, I ſay, all Spaws have their name, and natural property from the Minerals, or Metals they have diſſolved. As we call <hi>Knaisbrough
<pb facs="tcp:59064:7"/>Spaw a Vitrioline water,</hi> becauſe it has diſſolved <hi>Iron;</hi> ſo may I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly call <hi>Scarbrough Spaw a petri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying water,</hi> becauſe it has diſſolved Stone.</p>
            <p>If there be any doubt remaining unreſolved, touching the petrify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing property of <hi>Scarbrough Spaw;</hi> I beg but to know it from you, (that I may have no more to do with this man of words) and I ſhall be ready to give you that ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which reaſon will prompt me to.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only add a word of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy for my freedom, with <hi>Doctor Witty,</hi> the only provocation that I gave him, to all that uncivil lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage which he uſed towards me, was my oppoſing his opinion (which how fairly and candidly, the Book it ſelf can witneſs for me. But finding him in his return, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his ſtrength, rather in reviling,
<pb facs="tcp:59064:8"/>than diſputing; I was neceſſitated (contrary to my <hi>Genius</hi>) to uſe ſuch a way as might make him a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſenſible of himſelf; and yet in this I have not abounded too far, becauſe (for the moſt part) what might ſeem harſh, are but his own reflections, laid at his own dore, as the proper Father of them; and if there be any thing further, I am ſure it may be abundantly juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by his expreſſions towards me.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours Humble Servant,</hi> George Tonſtall.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:59064:8"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>ALL that I have writ againſt <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Spaw, is but the Symptom of a Melancholy ſancy <hi>(Pag. 125.)</hi> in the Judgment of <hi>Dr. Witty:</hi> to cure me of this, he has ſent me a bitter Pill; ſee now how finely he hath gilted it over; theſe are his laſt words, <hi>I do ſtill profeſs my ſelf to be a Friend to</hi> Dr. Tonſtall, <hi>and am ready to make it out, in any civil kindneſs; only (I hope) he will not henceforth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that I tell him any Secret.</hi> To reply to this, having dealt with him (as he ſays truly) like as <hi>Hanun</hi> did with <hi>David's</hi> Servants; he raiſes
<pb facs="tcp:59064:9"/>this note from <hi>2 Sam. 10.4. But this did ſo exceedingly diſoblige King</hi> David, <hi>that it became an occaſion of breaking the Bond of Friendſhip that had been betwixt them.</hi> Now may I trust him for a Friend, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est thou? As for mine expectance that he ſhould tell me any Secret, Alas, <hi>Mr. Culpepper</hi> has deluded mine hopes long ſince; for he having Tranſlated the <hi>London Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory,</hi> has rifled the Diſſectors <hi>Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net Counſels,</hi> and has laid open all his <hi>Secrets,</hi> to the view of all Engliſh-Men and Women; therefore let him be aſſured, I ſhall expect none from him.</p>
            <p>Another thing I deſire to note is, if the Diſſector rejoyn, he doth conſute his own Title. He calls his Book, <hi>An anſwer to all that I have writ, or ſhall hereafter write againſt</hi> Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough's Spaw. There is but one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy for this great Evil (he hints at
<pb facs="tcp:59064:9"/>it in the Epiſtle) He may chuſe a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, to re-inforce the Combat; and I ſhall take another, and let them fight it out, if there be any life left in his Cauſe. And that his Champion may have a fair Field to exerciſe his Valour in, and the most advantage imaginable, to rally up his ſcattered Forces; I have preſented, (in anſwer to <hi>p. 102.</hi>) Twelve Propoſitions, the <hi>Summa Totalis</hi> of all my Writings, concerning <hi>Scarbrough Spaw.</hi> Let him confute any one of theſe, and then I ſhall recant the Twelfth Propoſition, which is the neceſſary conſequence of them all.</p>
            <p>I have a word, or two more, to tell thee of <hi>Dr. Witty;</hi> Firſt, (It is an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of many years ſtanding) he commends <hi>Scarbrough Spaw</hi> good for all Diſeaſes; take theſe Inſtances for it. A <hi>Gentlewoman</hi> came from <hi>Lincolnſhire</hi> to <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> and had a Letter from her Phyſitian to Doctor
<pb facs="tcp:59064:10"/>
               <hi>Witty;</hi> yet ſhe ſent for me, deſiring to know my opinion. After ſhe had related her caſe, and asked whether I judged the Water to be good for her, or no; I demanded a reaſon of her, why ſhe ſent for me, for reſolution of that queſtion, being a stranger, and not of <hi>Dr. Witty,</hi> who was recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to her by Letter; ſays ſhe, <hi>We know the anſwer</hi> Dr. Witty <hi>gives to every one that comes to theſe Waters, before it be asked him;</hi> from hence is it (making the Spaw a Catholick remedy) that he aſſerts <hi>Philip Tranſel 10.51.</hi> That it cures the <hi>Aſthma, inveterate Catarrhs, Hecticks,</hi> and <hi>Conſumptions.</hi> I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, no otherwiſe, than as the <hi>King of Terrors</hi> doth; that is, a Cure for all Diſeaſes. <hi>Mr. Lampleugh</hi> live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a few Miles from <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> conſulted <hi>Dr. Witty,</hi> what he ſhould do to prevent an <hi>Hectick</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption,</hi> which he feared only he
<pb facs="tcp:59064:10"/>was inclined to; the <hi>Doctor</hi> forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with adviſed him to drink the Spaw, and kept him a fortnight at <hi>Mr. San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> houſe there, which ſuddenly brought upon him the thing he feared, who ſhortly after dyed of a Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. This his Mother-in-Law related to me, weeping. As for the <hi>Aſthma,</hi> the <hi>Lord Cr.</hi> came laſt year to <hi>Knaiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough,</hi> (who had ſound the Evil <hi>Scarbrough</hi> had done to him before) and related to me, how his Nephew was gone to <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> for cure of his Diſtemper, the <hi>Aſthma;</hi> I then told his <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> and deſired him to take notice of what I ſaid, that if the <hi>Squire</hi> drank a fortnight of thoſe Waters, it would undoubtedly deſtroy him, or elſe let him believe, that I have no judgment of the nature of <hi>Scarbrough Spaw.</hi> Coming to <hi>York</hi> after Spaw time, I enquired of <hi>Dr. Witty,</hi> how the Waters did with him; he gave me no other anſwer, but that
<pb facs="tcp:59064:11"/>he was very ill. I asked his <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> in Ordnary concerning him, and he told me, that the Waters did ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly diſagree with his Diſtemper, and as ſoon as he came to <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough,</hi> he did forbid him to drink of it. <hi>Mr. Atkinſon,</hi> formerly trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with a <hi>Heat</hi> and <hi>Scalding</hi> of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine (cauſed, according to <hi>Galen,</hi> by defluxion of ſharp Humours) ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed with <hi>Dr. Witty</hi> laſt year, for prevention of this Diſtemper; he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects him to drink <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which did ſo exceedingly aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate his Malady, that he was neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated to undergo the ſtrict rule of a Milk dyet, complaining to me of <hi>Dr. Witty</hi>'s bad counſel.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Scarbrough</hi> from its petrifying property is bad for the <hi>Stone, Gout,</hi> and <hi>Jaundice,</hi> ſo from its <hi>Saline Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of <hi>Nitre</hi> and <hi>Allom,</hi> it is an utter Enemy to all that are inclined to a <hi>Rheumatiſm,</hi> or that have an
<pb facs="tcp:59064:11"/>
               <hi>acidity</hi> in their blood; eſpecially if they be of a thin habit of body. This was the caſe of <hi>Two Gentlemen,</hi> that nearly ſcaped a miſchief by drinking of it; the one is <hi>Mr. Weſtby,</hi> who came to <hi>Scarbrough. Dr. Witty</hi> did prepare him for drinking the Waters, and though he ſubmitted to all his directions, yet the Waters did ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly diſorder him, that he was glad to deſiſt. Ever ſince he uſed <hi>Knaisbrough,</hi> and himſelf told me, that if he ſhould drink <hi>Scarbrough</hi> one fortnight, he was ſure it would abſolutely kill him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr. Weſtro</hi> (the other) came to us at <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> only to viſit his Friends, the two or three days he drank the Waters (not above two quarts at a time) did ſo far put him out of Tune, that he made his complaint to me, he could neither Eat, nor Sleep. It took me a weeks time before I could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce him to the ſtate of Health, which
<pb facs="tcp:59064:12"/>he had before he medled with the Waters.</p>
            <p>Let it be here noted the large dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the <hi>Acidity</hi> of either <hi>Nitre,</hi> or <hi>Allom,</hi> which <hi>Scarbrough</hi> partakes of; and that of <hi>Vitriol, Knaiſbrough</hi> is endewed with. <hi>This</hi> is ſo <hi>Connatural</hi> to the <hi>Ferment</hi> of the <hi>Stomach,</hi> that it <hi>agrees</hi> with all <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> and offends none, the other doth not ſo. Beſides, the <hi>Aci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity</hi> of <hi>Nitre</hi> and <hi>Allom frets;</hi> but this <hi>Heals</hi> from the property of <hi>Iron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mrs. Shaw</hi> of <hi>Ferrihill</hi> was (judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) gone in a Conſumption, having a continual Cough, and Expectorating little elſe but Blood, I adviſed her to <hi>Knaiſbrough</hi> Spaw; A Profeſſor of Divinity and Phyſick, told her Friends, 'twas the ready way to carry her to her Grave; yet ſhe followed my Counſel, and in a Fortnights time, the <hi>ſolutio continua</hi> in her Lungs
<pb facs="tcp:59064:12"/>was healed, ſhe perfectly recovered, and to this day continues healthful, and well-liking. So for this <hi>Balſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mick</hi> property of <hi>Knaisbrough</hi> (in <hi>Mr. Stanhope</hi> his Catalogue of Cures, performed by this Water) A relation of <hi>Mrs. Barker</hi> of <hi>Doar,</hi> and <hi>Mrs. Ellis</hi> of <hi>Beverley,</hi> both cured by it of a dangerous <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>leer in the Kidney.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Obſervation of <hi>Doctor Witty</hi> is, that what Diſtemper ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever any brings with them to <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough,</hi> if they drink the Waters, and find no <hi>preſent harm</hi> by it, but rather their <hi>Appetites</hi> mended, then muſt this be <hi>Regiſtred</hi> for a <hi>Cure</hi> done by <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Spaw.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>J. Br.</hi> firſt Lady, was afflicted for ſeveral years with the Jaundice, ſhe conſulted a Learned Phyſitian in <hi>York,</hi> who, by good helps, ſupported her, againſt the Extremities of that Diſtemper; her Ladiſhip took a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, without the conſent of her
<pb facs="tcp:59064:13"/>Phyſitian, to go to <hi>Scarbrough.</hi> Whilſt ſhe drunk the Waters, ſhe apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her ſelf a little lightſomer, and her ſtomach to meat better; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Doctor Witty</hi> records this in writing, as a cure of the <hi>Jaundice;</hi> the <hi>Lady</hi> getting notice thereof, with much ado, got her name expunged, telling <hi>Dr. Witty,</hi> ſhe would not be in Print. After her departure home, the Diſtemper returned violently up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her, in ſew weeks, her Ladyſhip dyed: This relation I had from her Phyſitian.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr. Thornton</hi> of <hi>Newton</hi> (his own Patient) was adviſed by him to drink the Waters, for the Paralitical Scurvy; which was done, ſays <hi>Dr. Witty, (pag. 166.) with eminent good ſucceſs, his ſtrength being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, and his ſpirits revived, ſo as he doth now enjoy again his perfect health.</hi> The next year I met with this Gentleman at <hi>Scarbrough,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:59064:13"/>who told me himſelf, that though he drunk the Waters, becauſe the <hi>Doctor</hi> would have him to do ſo, yet he found no good at all by them, but feared rather a declining in his condition, which fell out ſo, for ſoon after he dyed of his Diſtemper.</p>
            <p>I hope (Reader) though <hi>Dr. Witty</hi> be pleaſed to charge me with Levity, Diſ-ingenuity, Double dealing, and baſe ends, (and theſe repeated ſo often, that they become (like a Cramb recocta) troubleſom, and nautious to any Judicious perſon) For what I writ of <hi>Scarbrough Spaw,</hi> yet thou ſeeſt that the <hi>common good</hi> of men, the <hi>prevention</hi> of many evils may happen to the Sick, upon the frequent uſe of theſe Waters; and the <hi>vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> of a <hi>Truth</hi> of no ſmall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, are the motives that have inclined me to this undertaking. If he had (as becomed him) diſcourſed the difference betwixt us calmly, I
<pb facs="tcp:59064:14"/>had uſed no other dialect in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, than I did in my firſt Book, which is a ſufficient evidence, that I gave him no provocation, for all the Raileries he gives me; ſave only, that I became his Enemy for telling him the truth; which toucheth his Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold ſo nearly, that he fell into a fret, as he confeſſeth, <hi>(pag. 81.)</hi> Seeing therefore (to uſe his own expreſſion to <hi>Dr. S.)</hi> I am urged to go merrily on with him, I crave thine excuſe.</p>
            <p>As touching the anſwer <hi>Dr. S.</hi> gave a year ago, I ſhall only ſay, 'tis pity ſuch Green Fruit ſhould be plucked from the Tree; ſome further experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in his Library, and a little more time in his Library, will, I hope, produce riper fruit, and pleaſanter to the taſte of Judicious men, and Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars. He writ in haſte, and had not leiſure, nor opportunity to make tryal of two Experiments; concerning both which, I have now ſaved him a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,
<pb facs="tcp:59064:14"/>averring from Autopſia, firſt, that it is <hi>Glebe</hi> of <hi>Allom,</hi> that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipates in <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> and not the minera of <hi>Iron.</hi> And Secondly, That it is a needleſs thing to diſtil the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine of <hi>Scarbrough Spaw</hi> Drinkers, to ſeek for the <hi>Sabulous matter;</hi> for (if he take the Diſſectors opinion to be true) as it paſſeth all through Cap-paper, he makes no doubt, but it will do the like through our Bodies; ſo ſhall he find all the Sand in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine, which the Water did contain. If he believe his own Experiment, that the gentle Heat of Evaporation, will precipitate the Stone powder to the bottom of the Veſſel by a parity of Reaſon, much more will our Natural Heat (the acid fermence of the firſt and ſecond Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, furthering the ſeparation of Heterogenious parts of the Water) precipitate it in our Bowels.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59064:15"/>
            <p>His diſputing againſt <hi>Allom</hi> to be an <hi>Alkali,</hi> and <hi>Nitre</hi> to be an <hi>Acid,</hi> if all were granted to him, doth not ſo much as touch againſt the reaſon I gave, why <hi>Scarbrough</hi> doth not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifie wood put in it, after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of other ſuch like Waters. For (by his own confeſſion) there is an <hi>Acid</hi> and an <hi>Alkali</hi> in <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Water, which is all I demand to be granted; the thing therefore he hath gained, by oppoſing me in this is, that he hath occaſioned the Diſſector to break a jeſt upon us both.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Nitre</hi> is <hi>Filius ſolis,</hi> ſeen by his <hi>Red Garment.</hi> That a pound of <hi>Nitre</hi> will afford by diſtillation, a whole pound of an extream <hi>Acid Spirit;</hi> that it is, a <hi>Sulphurious infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable Salt,</hi> that mixt with the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kali</hi> of <hi>Tartar,</hi> it cauſeth a great <hi>Ebullition,</hi> are ſuch evidences to prove <hi>Nitre</hi> an <hi>Acid,</hi> that I judge Chymiſts will not deny them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59064:15"/>
            <p>That a <hi>Saponary</hi> quality is <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prium Quarto modo,</hi> to an <hi>Alkali,</hi> is granted of all. That <hi>Allom</hi> has ſuch a <hi>Lixiviate</hi> property, I may have a ſubſcription of all the <hi>Dyers</hi> in <hi>England</hi> to aver the ſame: Why then ſhould my Friend ſay, that <hi>it is no leſs than a palpable miſtake of me to ſay ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I will not contend with him further, only let me remember him, what is the ſaying of <hi>Cato,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Nulli tacuiſſe nocet.</l>
                  <l>Nocet eſſe Locutum.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:59064:16"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59064:16"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Diſſector Anatomized.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE firſt appearance of Doctor <hi>Witty</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, (<hi>pag.</hi> 1.) puts me in mind of a Souldier, that was juſtly baſtinaded for his faults, and when his haltings diſcovered his maims and hurts among his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Neighbours, he thought it his beſt policy to halt down right, more than he needed, and then to boaſt, that theſe hurts, were the evidences of his Valour, the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of his Proweſs and Manhood. Thus comes the <hi>Doctor</hi> upon the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59064:17"/>Stage, limping and halting, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of his bad uſage, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving it as a badge of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Vertue, in the rare diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries he hath made of <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Spaw; and this he ſets off with the ſaying off <hi>Themiſtocles, That while he was young, he was wont to ſay, that he had not yet done any thing notable; foraſmuch as he had not contracted envy, nor met with any oppoſition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If a man may contract envy for having a lame Leg, or for want of one Eye, then may this ſaying be applicable to <hi>Doctor Witty:</hi> I have only put to my hands, to keep theſe out of harms way, whom he by his Writings, would ſeduce into it. What I have done therefore, is properly a ſeaſonable oppoſition to his errors; and conſequently here is no evidence of his notable vertue.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:59064:17"/>
            <p n="2">2. He next tells us (<hi>p.</hi> 2.) how he had ſome thoughts of anſwering my Book, with <hi>à vidi &amp; Riſi,</hi> and makes as if it had deſerved no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Conſideration; becauſe weak in the <hi>Argument,</hi> and mean in the <hi>Deſign.</hi> This is a ſhort and eaſie way of Anſwering, and ſuch as I might beſtow upon his Book in the words of <hi>C. Hoffmannus</hi> to <hi>Romulus.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Legisti noſtrum, Riſiſti</hi> Romule <hi>librum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t vidi, &amp; Riſi,</hi> Romule <hi>dive tuum.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quae cauſa affectus paris, in tam diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare cauſa,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Riſisti ingenium tutè, ego ſtultitiam.</hi>
               </l> 
            </q>
            <p>Yet if he had contented himſelf herewith, <hi>as indeed,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>at the firſt he had thought to have done,</hi> then had he loſt his jeſt of the <hi>Cuccow,</hi> and (what is as conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able) an opportunity of telling the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59064:18"/>world the Pedigree of <hi>Galen;</hi> and how he has Crowned him King, and made Proclamation, that all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to Phyſick, who will not ſubſcribe to him the Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance and Supremacy alſo, ſhall not be called Sons of Art, but Baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>begoten, <hi>Quacks, Pſeu, Dochymiſts, Mountebanks,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe two Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derclaps, begets all the Fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments I met with in his Book. As for his pickering here and there with falſe Reports, fallacious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments, and frothy Repartees; they are no more to be valued, than a flap with a Fox tail, which <hi>Witty-like,</hi> he hath laid upon my back, and Dr. <hi>Simpſons</hi> in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Reader.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Dirt and Sand, which by Anatomizing the Water, I diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to be in <hi>Scarbrough Spaw,</hi> Dr. <hi>Witty</hi> undertakes, that he <hi>will cleanſe away,</hi> and ſays, <hi>though his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59064:18"/>work be like that of</hi> Hercules, <hi>when he purged the</hi> Augaean <hi>ſtable, yet his labour is nothing like his.</hi> In truth no, but like that of <hi>Siſiphus,</hi> in rowling the ſtone up Hill, which returned upon himſelf again.</p>
            <p>Now he begins with his Diſſect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing work; Dr. <hi>Witty</hi>'s Whittle, and <hi>Scanderbags</hi> Sword, are both of a Metal. Had the <hi>Doctor</hi> an arm like him, I ſhould be in more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger by this Diſſection, than when I was cut for the Stone.</p>
            <p>The firſt Paſs he makes is, (<hi>p.</hi> 3.) <hi>I have called him out to a publick Encounter, without any previous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation given on his ſide.</hi> It ſeems he may give ſtones inſtead of bread, yet muſt not be told on't. Is it not as free for me to declare mine Opinion, as for him to proclaim his. In writing of <hi>Scarbrough Spaw,</hi> I only medled with his Reaſons, forbearing unhandſom expreſſions;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59064:19"/>yet had I been ſharper towards him, I could have juſtified it from his Provocation; for I was deluded by his <hi>Hyperboles,</hi> and <hi>Male-deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of it, to drink of thoſe Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, to the hazard of a return in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my former Diſeaſe, the Stone, enough to ruine me and my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily. I ſuppoſe he did not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by deſign my coming thither, yet the harm I received, by drinking of it, was, <hi>Finis operis ejus,</hi> though not <hi>operantis.</hi> He tells us, (<hi>p.</hi> 4.)</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>He will in point of Friendſhip, mildly endeavour to clear up mine eye-ſight.</hi> I thank him for his love, but ſhall intreat him to make uſe of his own Spectacles; I need them not; a proof whereof I have given in that, during three days time, by Anatomizing the Water. I have diſcovered ſtone filings in it, which he could not ſee, in all the Thirty years he has been looking at it.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:59064:19"/>
            <p>He repeats what I ſaid, in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to my ſelf, of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Helmont.</hi> In reference to him, I ſay, they are too great lights for his weak Opticks; for in this caſe it is true, that <hi>minium ſenſibile deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it ſenſum.</hi> See p. 34. of Dr. <hi>Witty</hi>'s anſwer.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Marginal note is, <hi>Galen is ſleighted by me.</hi> I deſire the Reader to obſerve how he ſeeks, occaſions to pick a quarrel; unleſs he expects I ſhould put off my Hat every time I name <hi>Galen,</hi> I know no reaſon for his ſaying ſo; my words are theſe. <hi>Galens method of Phyſick, may juſtly be named ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, ſo far as he writes after the old man, his Maſters Copy; I dare not ſpeak further for him.</hi> Where is <hi>Galen</hi> ſlighted by this? I give him the ſame commendation that Dr. <hi>Witty</hi> gives him, in his Diſpute with Dr. S. all along he ſeems ſo to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59064:20"/>the word <hi>Rational</hi> to the <hi>Galenical method,</hi> as if Rational and Galenical, were <hi>Synonyma</hi> and <hi>convertibilia;</hi> 'tis true, he intends to exclude the Chymical method, as Empirical, which cannot be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him; for if thoſe Diſeaſes be cured by this method, which the Galenical method leaves as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable; certainly ſuch Natural ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects muſt be produced by moſt rational mediums. But that <hi>Galen</hi> hath oppoſed <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing ſo much to the four firſt qualities, both as to the cauſes and method of curing Diſeaſes, is ſo vulgarly known by his Book, <hi>De antiqua Medicina;</hi> that I need not mention it to the Learned; neither doth Doctor <hi>Witty</hi>'s Encomium of <hi>Galen,</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 12. where he ſays, <hi>He was the prime ſtar of the firſt mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude in his Orb</hi>) any more than eclipſe his Honour. 'Tis no leſs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59064:20"/>than treaſon in him, to ſpeak ſo ſlightingly of <hi>Galen;</hi> for if but a Star, from what Sun hath he borrowed his Splendour? ſurely from one of my two great Lights. Thus <hi>good Wits jump;</hi> I ſhall not trouble the Reader to Comment upon this his Digreſſion, to <hi>p.</hi> 14. All which is tranſlated out of <hi>Lambeſius;</hi> only let this vain brag be noted, <hi>p.</hi> 11. <hi>Galen has brought the Art of Phyſick to ſuch a Perfection, as no Art in the world can pretend to.</hi> Mr. <hi>Stubbs</hi> is modeſt in his Writings, againſt the <hi>Royal Society,</hi> compared with this one poſition of the Diſſector; which if true, proclaims all thoſe of their Society, that are Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Fools and Madmen. 'Twere happy for the City and Country of <hi>York,</hi> if Doctor <hi>Witty</hi>'s practice could confirm their belief, of this perfection in his Art. <hi>If others can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not underſtand</hi> (Galen) <hi>well,</hi> as he
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59064:21"/>ſays (I ſuppoſe) he means in the Greek Copy, to be ſure he doth; but <hi>I deſire to treat him as a Friend,</hi> and therefore do commend to his reading, <hi>Petrus Severinus Danus,</hi> his <hi>Idaea Medicina, and ſo ſet him right in his way</hi> to Perfection.</p>
            <p>Doctor <hi>Witty, (p.</hi> 15.) Cavils at my expreſſion of <hi>ſe defendendo,</hi> and thus he vents it; <hi>Really I wonder at this expreſſion, whoever offended him that he ſhould ſtand upon his defence, &amp;c.</hi> May not the Reader ſee by this, how hardly he ſtrains to get ſomething to talk; I refer it to the conſtruction of any man, if more could be intended by that innocent expreſſion, than to ſignifie that I meddle not with his Books, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than was neceſſary to defend this one poſition, <hi>That the nature of</hi> Scarbrough Spaw <hi>is petrifying:</hi> In the ſame Page, he ſhews his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure at this paſſage; Dr. <hi>Witty</hi>'s
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59064:21"/>
               <hi>failure was, that he left off where he ſhould have begun.</hi> I perſiſt in the ſame mind ſtill, he ſhould firſt have Anatomized the Water, that he might have viewed what was contained diſtinctly in its bowels; but this work he leaves to others. Doctor S. gives a reaſon for his ſo doing, (<hi>pag.</hi> 145.) <hi>Not for want of Ignorance,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>in the Critical Analyſis of the water.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But why ſhould Dr. <hi>Witty</hi> be ſo angry for this charge truly laid againſt him? doth it not argue <hi>much ill Nature, and little Judgment,</hi> to reject neceſſary advice. But wherein am I to be blamed that gave it? except only that it came too late.</p>
            <p>The next Marginal Note (<hi>p.</hi> 16.) is, Dr. <hi>T. Diſingenious towards the Author.</hi> I know who it was that laid on theſe black patches, intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, thereby to beautifie the face of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59064:22"/>Dr. <hi>Witty</hi>'s ill-favour'd diſcourſe; 'tis an ugly Epithite, which I hate worſe, than to be called a Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, I ſhall therefore clear my ſelf of it. I ſaid in my Preface, that Dr. <hi>Witty,</hi> after he had obſerved what was moſt conſpicuous about the <hi>Spaw,</hi> and tryed that the Gall Tinctured the Water, contents himſelf with fair probabilities for aſſerting his Five Principles. I appeal to the Reader; if I have dealt diſingeniouſly with him, in ſaying ſo, I have given the Title of fair probabilities to his proofs; but he is not pleaſed therewith, but will have them <hi>called Arguments of Demonſtration.</hi> Though they were all proved to be Fallacies (as may be ſeen in my Book) touching <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol</hi> and <hi>Iron,</hi> the Principles in difference betwixt us. As for Salt, another Principle of his, he ſaith, for it, (<hi>p.</hi> 19.) <hi>The propinquity of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59064:22"/>Sea gives ground to many wiſe men, to think it may have Salt,</hi> though he knows there are ſeveral freſh Springs about <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> which are as near the Sea, as the <hi>Spaw</hi> is. Beſides, ſee <hi>Norwoods</hi> Relation to the <hi>Royal Society, (p.</hi> 565.) affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that at <hi>Bermudas</hi> they dig Wells of freſh Water, ſometimes within twenty yards of the Sea.</p>
            <p>He concludes (<hi>p.</hi> 20.) that I have <hi>dealt with him, as</hi> Hanun <hi>did with King</hi> David<hi>'s meſſenger, citing the place of Scripture,</hi> 2 Sam. 10.4. How can I help that? Truth is not aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to appear naked in publick, though the Diſſector be; 'tis true, he received an anſwer againſt Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol and Iron, being in the Spaw, importing no leſs than the ſhaving of the half of his Beard, enough to render him ridiculous; and the laying open the ſtone filings by the Anatomy of the water, was like
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59064:23"/>the cutting of his Garments in the middle, even to his buttocks. It ſeems, indeed, he was aſhamed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, and therefore he writes a Letter to the <hi>Royal Society,</hi> preſenting them with ſeven or eight Extracts and Spirits, which he took out of <hi>Scarbrough Spaw;</hi> yet hath the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence to ſay, <hi>it was not Candidly done of me, to mention that of try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Gall, and to leave out the reſt of his Experiments (expreſſed in this Letter)</hi> for other, I know none. This letter was Printed four months after my Book come forth, yet he blames me for leaving it out; I beg his pardon, becauſe I do not pretend to that infallible Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Spirit, which Doctor <hi>Witty</hi> aſſumes to himſelf; ſo as to anſwer all that he <hi>ſhall hereafter write,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I read what is written: But I owe him the kindneſs of a Friend, and therefore ſhall now take notice
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59064:23"/>of it, <hi>N. L.</hi> Firſt, he is not pleaſed with Dr. <hi>Foot, in mentioning his principles of</hi> Scarbrough, <hi>(Iron, Allom, Nitre) that he pretermitted Vitriol; yet he preſumes it was not upon deſign;</hi> as if Water could per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of Iron, and yet Vitriol be abſent from it; 'tis a grand Solaeciſm in Chymiſtry. Secondly, As touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Vitriol, he refers to his Book; <hi>yet</hi> (ſays he) <hi>it is moſt conſpicuous at the Well.</hi> A loud untruth, for it is a Nitrous Salt only that is ſo; for all that ſproots out of the Hill, ſhoots in Stirias, the ſign which he himſelf gives for Nitre, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no difference betwixt that which he calls Vitriol, and that he calls Nitre, but Colour only. Now I demand, <hi>ſeeing his leaſure did permit him to ſtep to</hi> Scarbrough <hi>to renew his Experiments, there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving to be more Critical, why he omitted</hi> to preſent this he calls Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59064:24"/>ſo conſpicuous to the <hi>Royal Society:</hi> doubtleſs his return with this, would have been more ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory to them, than the ſeven or eight ſorts of Extracts, and Spirits, which now I come to examine. <hi>His firſt Extract. Exhale</hi> Scarbrough <hi>Water, till all the moiſture be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, and there remains a Body of Minerals ſigned. A.</hi> See his Book (<hi>p.</hi> 10.) and how he defends it in his anſwer, <hi>(p.</hi> 22.) to be an Extract. Will not the Apothecary Boys laugh at him for this? if when he preſcribes to them Extract of Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, they ſhould ſend Pillulae Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiae; the Patient will find a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between them, though Dr. <hi>Witty</hi> makes none. His ſecond Extract. <hi>Diſſolve the firſt Extract in water, and filter it, there will remain a little Juſipid-earth.</hi> Pray why did he not ſign at <hi>B.</hi> Oh the cunning of Dr. <hi>Witty,</hi> this is the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59064:24"/>very Critical Point, the foundation of all the diſpute betwixt him and me; the main pillar on which I build all my diſcourſe; an Extract which I made out of <hi>Scarbrough Spaw,</hi> not before ſo duly taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of; yet muſt it be hid from the eyes of the <hi>R. S.</hi> whoſe ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction he is ambitious to court, and only paſs it over with this ſlight remembrance, but not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it to them; calling that a little Inſipid earth, which is a great deal of Gretty ſtone powder. How juſtly may I retort his own words upon him? <hi>What makes all this double<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dealing for advantage?</hi> He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds, <hi>Evaporate that Water away, there is the Body</hi> B. <hi>this I judge to be for the greater part Nitre: diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve this Body in Water, and filter it, and there remains in the paper powder</hi> C. <hi>which ſeems to be the aluminous part.</hi> Why ſo? may not
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59064:25"/>the Aluminous Salt in the Water, as eaſily paſs through the Filter, as the Nitre; <hi>This is ſometimes found to be like a Chryſtalline Sand,</hi> C. C. Take heed of it,
'tis better expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed (<hi>p.</hi> 64.) the groſſer part of the Minerals or Metals which the fire fixes. <hi>Evaporate this Water, and there is a Salt Dor, that</hi> D. D. <hi>the difference betwixt them, is in the degrees of Heat; this diſſolved again, and evaporated, there is a Salt</hi> D. D. D. <hi>When the</hi> Spaw <hi>Water is firſt ſet on the fire, there falls to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom a Yellowiſh Powder</hi> E. He can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay what it is I told him (<hi>p.</hi> 56.) of my Book, that it was the Glebe of Allom, which appears in a Black Powder, if the Water be ſet by cold, after two or three days, <hi>N. L.</hi> Dr. <hi>Witty</hi> being reproved for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting his Five Principles, before he had Anatomized the Water; he now (to make amends) will diſſect
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59064:25"/>it into more parts, than makes up the whole eight Extracts ſigned, <hi>A. B. C. C. D D. D. E.</hi> he ſhould have proceeded in the Alphabet to <hi>Witty,</hi> that the <hi>R. S.</hi> might ſee he had not his name for naught. Now I appeal to the Reader, what more he hath made to appear, by all theſe, then a Nitro Aluminous Salt (which is impoſſible, by Art, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate aſunder) except Sand and Clay, which Doctor <hi>Witty</hi> will not have ſpoken on. <hi>He calcin'd alſo the Body of Minerals ſigned</hi> F. I demand if there were any Flakes of Iron interſperced amongſt it, as he told us there were, in his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to <hi>Hydr. Chym. p.</hi> 67. He af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms in the place fore-cited, that they do Calcine whitiſh; now ſays he, <hi>you may ſee they have a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt appearance of a Red Colour,</hi> qui color albus erat nunc eſt, <hi>&amp;c. This Rediſh Colour he judges to come
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59064:26"/>from Iron,</hi> and for that purpoſe he preſented it; whereas it is a better Argument, that the Redneſs comes from the Sand and Clay that is in it, which by ſtreſs of fire, turns to be of that Colour, as is obſerved in the Potters furnace, and Brick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kilns he preſented; alſo half an Ounce of the Spirit, beſides an Ounce of Phlegm which he diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out of ſix Ounces of the body of Minerals, ſigned by <hi>G. H.</hi> Alas, that a man ſhould be at all this pains and charge, only to confute himſelf, and that before the <hi>Royal Society,</hi> to whom he makes this offering, and of whom he boaſts, <hi>theſe noble Worthies were pleaſed to receive with ſome ſatisfaction.</hi> I deſire no better Judges, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore appeal to them, if it be not impoſſible to diſtil a Spirit of half an Ounce, out of ſix Ounces of this Body of Minerals, unleſs it be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59064:26"/>granted that there is a large pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of Sand and Clay in it, as I have affirmed.</p>
            <p>For what elſe could hinder the Salts from fluxing in the Retort, and if they did flux, how could the Spirit ariſe in the Receiver?</p>
            <p>Now let others judge (to uſe his own words) with a little alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if theſe few Notes may not ſerve <hi>for Academical Demonstrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of</hi> Doctor Witty<hi>'s Mechanical Fooleries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Marginal Note (<hi>p.</hi> 23.) is, <hi>he confeſſes his Levity.</hi> I confeſſed my credulity, that I durſt drink the Waters, and commend them to others, upon the credit of <hi>Doctor Witty</hi>'s Book. Forgive me but this once; when after ſearch I found Stone-powder in it, I then ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally deſiſted, and diſſwaded o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, enclined either to Stone, Gout, or Jaundice, from further
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59064:27"/>medling with thoſe Waters. He ſays, <hi>I brought my Wife thither,</hi> what then? it was not for Cure of any of theſe three Diſeaſes mentioned; <hi>ergo,</hi> his talk is, <hi>nihil ad rombum;</hi> but of this more anon.</p>
            <p>But that this charge of Levity might the better take place in the minds of men, he ſtrengthens it with another, plainly inſinuating, <hi>p.</hi> 24. that the change of my opinion was but for a baſe deſign, of inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and advantage; and thus he doth above nine times (if I miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reckon not) in his Book. What ſhall I anſwer to this? will <hi>Doctor Witty</hi> arrogate to himſelf the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of my Heart and Principles? he knows whoſe ſole prerogative it is to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, may not I with equal probability affirm, that 'tis a baſe deſign of gain in him, to plead for <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> againſt the evidences produced of its danger,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59064:27"/>to ſuch as drink it. But I would have him know (if he hath the Ingenuity of believing a ſerious Profeſſion) that the Conviction I have of the hazard, that attends the drinking thoſe Waters, was the true cauſe that moved me to a publick diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of it; if theſe Accuſations be <hi>friendly or manly</hi> (they are his own words) <hi>I know not what is friendly or humane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What he further urgeth (<hi>pag.</hi> 26. 27.) that <hi>Scarbrough Spaw</hi> cannot have a petrifying property from Nitre, is ſo altogether nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, that one would think he had not read my Book, which he pretends to anſwer; neither is his catch about a <hi>Nitrous ſtone, (p.</hi> 28.) worthy of any conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>Saxum Nitroſum,</hi> is <hi>Kirchers</hi> expreſſion, and <hi>Salt-peter,</hi> is in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine called <hi>Sal-petrae.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:59064:28"/>
            <p>But now he falls on at laſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my firſt Argument (to prove the petrifying property of <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough</hi>) drawn from the Authority of <hi>Kircher,</hi> which he thus anſwers, <hi>Kircher is ſuch an uncertain, and wavering Writer, that my Argument, from his Authority, is of no validity at all.</hi> This is a great unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs in Dr. <hi>Witty,</hi> thus to abuſe this Learned Author, that ſtood him in ſo much ſtead before; ſo long as <hi>Kircher</hi> ſeemed to be on his ſide, againſt Dr. <hi>S.</hi> then who but <hi>Kircher, Paracelſus</hi> was not worthy to carry his Books, <hi>who was certainly a hundred times more profoundly Learned than he.</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to <hi>Hydr. chym p.</hi> 228. Now that he is turned to be on my ſide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Dr. <hi>Witty,</hi> he is a wavering and uncertain Author; well, what then? is his Authority, therefore, of no validity at all? If Dr. <hi>Witty</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:59064:28"/>could produce the Authority of <hi>Galen</hi> againſt me, I would an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>Valeat quantum valere po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test.</hi> The Authority of this Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man is of ſome weight, until he bring as great a Scholar to put in the other Scale to ballance it; let it be obſerved, that authority of Authors, is the beſt weapon Dr. <hi>Witty</hi> has to contend with; and if any dare encounter the <hi>Doctor,</hi> none doth more induſtriouſly han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle this weapon than he. But I ſhall further concern my ſelf to vindicate <hi>Kircher,</hi> from another charge of Dr. <hi>Witty: Kircher is extremely roving and unreſolved, wherein this petrifying property ſhall reſide,</hi> ſays he, (<hi>p.</hi> 28.) Oh ſtrange! Self-intereſt is of ſuch a ſmoaky nature and force, that it puts out his Eyes; and therefore he cannot ſee, how in the very ſame Book and Chapter quoted by him, he
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59064:29"/>placeth the petrifying property of waters in their diſſolving of Stone; and that to effect this Diſſolution, 'tis neceſſary ſome Salt (of what ſort ſoever) be joyned to the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>lib.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 46. there are theſe words, <hi>Succus Lapidificus eſt ſaxum nitroſum, aqua eliquatum, quod ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perientia docet, ſi enim aqua nitro vel tartaro miſcetur &amp; polliui ſaxi per filtrum colaveris illa frondes ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milia<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nitida, cortice ſaxeo veſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, quod ſine ſale non eveniet, unde patet, vel ſalis nitri, vel aluminis copiam jungi debere aquis rupes per currentibus, ad petrificationem.</hi> He ſpeaks ſo plain, that he that runs may read, that any Salt in water will ſerve to diſſolve Stone, and thereby make the water to petrifie; and that no Salt of what ſort ſoever, that is in water, and has not diſſolved Stone, is petrifying. Reader, you ſee how diſingeniouſly <hi>Dr. Witty</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:59064:29"/>hath dealt with <hi>Kircher,</hi> and that he is ſo far from weakning his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, that he diſcovers only, that either he would not, or did not underſtand him.</p>
            <p>My ſecond Argument is, Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment, whereby I prove that <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough</hi> is parallel to all petrifying waters, in that property which is eſſential to them; namely, in that they have diſſolved Stone, which is common to no other water, which is not petrifying. I inſtance in <hi>Knaisbroughs Dropping Well;</hi> what ſays Dr. <hi>Witty</hi> to this? <hi>To both theſe Arguments</hi> (of Authority, and of Experiment) <hi>I'le anſwer, ſaith he, in one word,</hi> why in one word? I ſhall dare him, or any man elſe, to confute me, as the Scholar confuted <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> with ſaying, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> thou lyeſt. Upon this Point, I'le venture as high as Dr. <hi>Witty</hi> has done, to give up the cauſe. If I be
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59064:30"/>falſe in either of my Experiments, which I have made of <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> and of this Dropping Well; but let him ſpeak out, <hi>Knaisbrough will cover with a ſtony Cruſt, Moſs put into it; and let any man ſhew me that</hi> Scarbrough <hi>will do ſo, and I'le give up the Cauſe.</hi> What a ſorry un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Scholar-like vaunt is this, when I told him before, that <hi>Scarbrough</hi> was not accuſed by me, for doing ſo, if they agreed in this Point; how could he and I diſpute ſuch a matter, which any two Girls that come to the Waters, may decide with their eyes? It could not then be a fit ſubject for Diſputation; but though it petrifies not a ſtick put in it, what if it petrifies when put in our Bodies, and leaves a cruſt of Stone, when 'tis paſſing through, in our Vital Bowels? It will not follow, that becauſe it doth not the one, therefore it cannot do the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59064:30"/>other; there is a difference in the ſubjects, Sticks and Living fleſh are not one; there is a difference in the object, the water in the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain is Homogenical; every drop of that water, is water, and will ſo paſs through the filter, but after it is received into our Bodies, the Ferments of Concoction makes a ſeparation of the Principles, and what was before Water, is now in part, Sand and Clay. But this is all nothing in <hi>Dr. Witty</hi>'s account; I hope the Learned will judge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe of it; with this empty brag, he would paſs on to my Third Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument: I ſhall not part with him ſo, but ſhall fetch him hither, from <hi>p.</hi> 57. (Dr. <hi>Witty</hi> has diſſected me after ſuch a Butcherly manner, that I am forced to make Head and Pluck go together.)</p>
            <p>There he concludes thus, <hi>The parallel betwixt Dropping Well and</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:59064:31"/>Scarbrough, <hi>is naught and frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous.</hi> You would think a ſtrong Team of Arguments went before, that made this concluſion follow; 'tis this, <hi>The ſalt of Dropping Well is not Nitre, for it does not ſhoot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Stirias:</hi> ſuppoſe it were ſo, that the Water of <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> and <hi>Dropping Well</hi> have different Salts, what is this to the purpoſe, ſo long as they agree in this, that they both have diſſolved Stone? 'Tis proved already, let the Salt be what it will, whereby the water has power to diſſolve ſtone, that water is petri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying. Seeing in this therefore, they do agree, wherein the petri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying property of all Waters doth recide; I have all granted to me I diſpute for, but I declare and vow, <hi>per fidem meam datam uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitati Oxon,</hi> that the Salt of <hi>Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Well</hi> is Nitrous, and ſhoots into Stirias, having it to ſhew to any
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59064:31"/>that queſtions this my ſolemn pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, enough, I hope, to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie any Brother of the Profeſſion, but the Diſſector. He proceeds, (becauſe I declare there is Nitre in Scarbrough) <hi>I have proved it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, to be inconſiſtent with the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and property of Nitre to make a ſtone;</hi> who goes about to diſprove him in this? he is beating the Air again.</p>
            <p>Reader, then ſee that <hi>Scarbrough</hi> and <hi>Dropping Well</hi> are parallel; for any thing the Diſſector has to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject againſt it, hear him now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs it; ſays he, (<hi>pag.</hi> 56.) of the <hi>Dropping Well, if it be evapourated away, it leaves in the bottom of the veſſel a gretty ſtone powder;</hi> ſo doth <hi>Scarbrough</hi> (confeſſed of all hands that have tryed it) <hi>ergo,</hi> they are parallel. Dr. <hi>Witties</hi> Friend con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to me, he boiled <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Water this year, and found it did
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59064:32"/>ſo. But this is not all, as he has confeſſed that <hi>Scarbrough</hi> and <hi>Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Well</hi> are parallel, here now he gives up the whole Cauſe; his next words are, <hi>For the fire fixes the Lapideſcent juice;</hi> hence this Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſm doth naturally reſult.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Water, that after evaporation leaves a gretty ſtone powder at the bottom of the Veſſel, has in it a Lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcent juice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But</hi> Scarbrough Spaw, <hi>after eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration, leaves a gretty ſtone powder at the bottom of the Veſſel;</hi> ergo,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Spaw has in it a Lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcent juice.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is his own confeſſion in the place force-cited, (<hi>p.</hi> 56.) The <hi>minor</hi> is proved by the Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment mentioned, and confeſſed by all Experimentators of <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Spaw; <hi>nemine contradicente.</hi> It is ſuperfluous to ſay more, yet for ſatisfaction of the vulgar, I ſhall ſay again,</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:59064:32"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> Spaw <hi>that has in it a Lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcent juice, is a petrifying water.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But</hi> Scarbrough Spaw <hi>has in it a Lapideſcent juice;</hi> ergo,</p>
            <p>Scarbrough Spaw <hi>is a petrifying Water.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reader, now that mine Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, the Diſſector, is under my Feet, as I am a Gentleman, I ſcorn to trample upon him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall with all ſubmiſſion, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently give him leave to pull the hood over mine Ears, in the moſt diſgraceful manner to degrade me, if the minor Propoſition of the firſt Syllogiſm prove not true upon his own tryal and experiment.</p>
            <p>My third Argument, <hi>à priori,</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 30.) from the <hi>apporhoea ſpiritus Lapidifici,</hi> is now, <hi>ex ſupra abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danti;</hi> ſo that if there were no effects of this to be ſeen on the Cliff, Dr. <hi>Witty's</hi> boaſting is vain, though he be got up as high as
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59064:33"/>
               <hi>Tenderdens Steeple.</hi> I adviſe him to make uſe of the Bell-rope, and the <hi>Muſcle ſhells we find petrified on the bank,</hi> he ſays, <hi>was caſt up by the Sea.</hi> So may be, was the three Cart load of Earth, that lies petrified, at the bottom of the Hill; but hear his proof, <hi>Aſſuredly the Sea doth petrifie any thing that has in it a Lapideſcent juice,</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 31.) This is a Golden Aphoriſm, ſo doth all the four Elements, Fire, Air, Earth, and Water, without Salt; for Fire, that is his own ſaying, (<hi>p.</hi> 56.) the words that coſt him ſo dear before cited. For Air, ſee <hi>Tachen. p.</hi> 15. where he ſays, that 'tis obſerved, that a Flint ſtone, laid on the ground, of a hundred pound weight, will receive from the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bient Air ſuch nouriſhment, that yearly, it will acquire about ten pound more weight; for Water look into freſh rivers, how full they
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59064:33"/>are of pebble ſtones at the bottom; for Earth dig any where among the Quarries. Is not this then ſpok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en like a Philoſopher think you? hear him now, how like a Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian he utters his mind; <hi>Hence it comes to paſs, that he that has any La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pideſcent juice, which we call a Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarous humour, ſhall ſooner contract the stone, if he eat much ſalt with his meat.</hi> This is point blank a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the unqueſtionable reaſons, and experience of <hi>Helmont, cap. de Lithiaſi,</hi> 3. <hi>parog.</hi> 30. <hi>Sexagenarium immunem arenum calculo ſervavi annos ſedecim (cui alioqui obnoxius erat) largo ſalis marim uſu, quod deinceps in multis confirmavi.</hi> But Dr. <hi>Witty</hi> matters not what <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont</hi> ſay; for he told me (I hope, not for a ſecret) when I was at <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> and he newly come from <hi>Cambridge</hi> in Triumph, for his victory over Dr. S. That <hi>Helmont
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59064:34"/>was a Quack,</hi> and if he could have met with the man, that Married his Daughter, whom he ſought af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in <hi>London,</hi> he aſſured me, That Son-in-Law of his, would ſay no leſs of him. I ſhall therefore tell him the practice of another Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Phyſician and Chymiſt, famous for his Cures done in the North, Doctor <hi>Webb:</hi> he for preventing of Tartarous humours, coagulating in the Body, did uſe himſelf, and adviſed all his Friends to break-faſt every morning, with Bread and Salt; which was obſerved in his time, by moſt Gentlemen of his acquaintance: I dare be poſitive, that this breakfaſt, is a better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt for the Stone, than the eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Radiſh Roots with Meat, which Dr. <hi>Witty</hi> magnifies for a ſecret, (<hi>p.</hi> 61.)</p>
            <p>But if any object, that Salt meats are found to be ill for the Stone,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59064:34"/>I'll grant it; yet doth it not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore follow, that to eat much Sea-Salt, with freſh meat, is ſo, as <hi>Dr. Witty</hi> ſaith, for this reaſon. If meat be laid in Salt, before it be eaten, the longer it lies, the more of the fleſhes Alkali is melted into the Salt, (which we find again by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilling of the pickle) The fleſh being ſo much deprived of this, muſt therefore be bad for the Stone, in as much as Acidity in all Concoctions, but the firſt is the principle of Coagulation, and Alkali is the ſole ſweetner of it: If this be not a Note above Ela in <hi>Doctor Witty</hi>'s Gamut, I would have him to dance, after this my pipe, for the future.</p>
            <p>That this Diſſector is a perfect Trifler, we have a proof of it, as all along; ſo here, becauſe I did but allude to <hi>Lot</hi>'s Wife, what a busſle he makes about her, writing
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59064:35"/>in Folio to <hi>Doctor Bazere</hi> for infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, whether it was Sea-ſalt, or other Mineral that ſhe was turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into; yea, ſo Fool-hardy is <hi>Doctor Witty,</hi> that he will preſcribe to the Almighty a reaſon of his miraculous doings. Says he, <hi>She was not turned into Marine Salt, for then ſhe would have melted away with every ſhower, and ſo it could not have ſuted with the deſign of God.</hi> Vain man, the ſame Omnipotent hand, that with-held the Buſh that burned with fire, that it was not conſumed, would have kept the Salt from melting with rain, and made it ſute his deſign, as long as he pleaſed. But to go on, <hi>Doctor Bazere</hi> ſends this Letter of <hi>Doctor Witty</hi>'s to the <hi>Biſhops Chaplain;</hi> He told me that a Traveller, lately ſhewed him a white lump of ſtone, like Alabaſter, bidding him to taſte it; he did ſo; ſays the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59064:35"/>to him, that is a piece of <hi>Lot's</hi> Wife; upon this report, the Chaplain fell a ſpitting and a ſpawl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſeeming to be angry, that he was not told ſo before he put his tongue to it; for ſays he, for ought you know, it was taken out of her Buttock. Had this Traveller gone to <hi>Doctor Witty</hi> with it, he would (to give the world ſatisfaction) have lick't his lips at it, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it had been ſo.</p>
            <p>To let this Woman alone, I ſay, old <hi>Parr,</hi> who lived an hundred and forty years, and eat Sea-ſalt with his meat daily, when he could get it, if <hi>Doctor Witty</hi> ſpeak truth, that this Salt is petrifying, then 'twas a miracle, like that of <hi>Lots</hi> Wife, that he was not turned into a petrifying Pillar of Salt before he dyed.</p>
            <p>Whilſt <hi>Doctor Witty</hi> is of this opinion, it were advice, <hi>ſecundùm
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59064:36"/>artem,</hi> for him to perſwade people to eat their meat without Salt.</p>
            <p>He comes next to my fourth Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, from the effects of <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough</hi> Spaw, inſtancing firſt in my ſelf, how hurtful theſe Waters were to me; he brings in with it, what I ſaid of <hi>Knaisbrough</hi> before, how it brought mucous matter out of my Bladder, which I illuſtrated with a ſaying of <hi>Helmont</hi> in his <hi>Cuſtos errans,</hi> (p. 212.) <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des malè ſe habent continuo plorant partem proprii alimenti, quod ſibi aſſimilare debebant:</hi> The Marginal note is, <hi>Dr. T. Cites</hi> Helmont <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinently,</hi> (p. 34.) yea, ſaith he, <hi>The matter for which I cite him, and the words, agree like a Harp and an Harrow.</hi> Now, if I produce a another place in <hi>Helmont,</hi> where the words, and the matter, are both expreſly together, <hi>Doctor Witty</hi> had better ſaid nothing. See <hi>Delithiaſi,</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:59064:36"/>(p. 664.) <hi>Oblaeditur nempe veſica in ſua digeſtione acrudeli &amp; molesto hoſpite calculo, qua-propter impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, partem ſui alimenti indigeſtam, continuo plorat, quia preficere, atque promovere eam nequit novam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ideo accerſit ſucceſſive.</hi> It appears then, that though in the judgment of <hi>Dr. Witty, Helmont</hi> is impertinent to write thus, yet have not I cited him impertinently; <hi>Nor doth it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear,</hi> ſays he, <hi>that I underſtand</hi> Helmonts <hi>meaning.</hi> I deſerve a Fools Coat, if I do not; <hi>To ſay no more</hi> (ſays he) <hi>than what appears true to Learned men, this is one of thoſe ſentences, wherein</hi> Helmont <hi>affects obſcurity, and is ſcarce intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligible.</hi> Thus <hi>Dr. Witty</hi> would put the Fools Cap upon the Head of all Learned men, meaſuring their knowledge by his own: <hi>Cuſtodes</hi> is the one hard word that is in the ſentence; he knew the whole body
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59064:37"/>is diſtinguiſhed into three, <hi>Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentia, Contenta, &amp; impetum fati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia;</hi> what ailed him, that he could not appropriate the word <hi>Cuſtodes,</hi> to the laſt of theſe? doth not the Spirits <hi>Animal, Vital,</hi> and <hi>Natural</hi> (as they ſay) deſerve to be called <hi>Cuſtodes,</hi> ſeeing they are the Fountain of all the Functions, which every part of the body doth perform. <hi>Dr. Witty,</hi> in that he can ſmell Vitriol in an Allom Water diſtinctly, hath approved himſelf to be <hi>Homo Emuniti naris;</hi> yet ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he catch a cold in his head this Winter, and thereupon water diſtils out of his Alimbick, and wets his Handkerchief daily; if this experience doth not teach him to underſtand <hi>Helmonts</hi> words I cited, then for certain there is ſomething elſe (his brains) has dropt out of his Noſe. What weeds <hi>Doctor Witty</hi> can gather out of <hi>Helmont,</hi> I know
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59064:37"/>not; ſure I am, this ſentence of his is a <hi>Flower,</hi> that is fragrant in the Noſtrils of all Artiſts, whilſt they have to do with moſt Diſeaſes, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly the Diabetes, Stone in the Bladder, all Ulcers, inward and outward.</p>
            <p>He ſays, <hi>I had the ſame reaſon to charge</hi> Knaisbrough <hi>Water for breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the mucous matter that it brought away, as to charge</hi> Scarbrough <hi>for breeding the Stone.</hi> Let <hi>Dr. Witty</hi> give me as good a reaſon for the former, how is it poſſible that a <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trioline</hi> water ſhould breed Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous water in the Bladder, as I have done in the latter, how <hi>Scarbrough</hi> water is apt to breed the Stone, and then I'le believe he writes ſenſe.</p>
            <p>I ſaid before, that <hi>Nitre</hi> in <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough,</hi> is as the <hi>Roſe;</hi> ſtone filings are the <hi>prickles</hi> that grow with it. This is good, the other is bad, yea,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59064:38"/>the worſt thing in the world for the Stone.</p>
            <p>He tells me, (<hi>p.</hi> 37.) out of <hi>Kir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher,</hi> that I had reaſon to look for fits of Stone, after cutting. 'Tis granted, and therefore I came to <hi>Scarbrough</hi> to prevent them, where I met with thoſe fits, and upon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of the Water, I found juſt cauſe to ſay it bred them. Mine experience confirms what I ſaid; for ſince I was cut for the Stone, I never, to this day, felt the leaſt ſymptom of Gravel, ſave only, when I drunk of <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Water, and immediately after the drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it.</p>
            <p>But ſays he, <hi>Scarbrough by reaſon of the Nitre in it, makes a plentiful Current run through the paſſages of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine, and therefore cannot breed the ſtone.</hi> At firſt it doth ſo, till it take a Jadiſh Fit, ſooner or la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it will neither go backward by
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59064:38"/>Stool, nor forward by Urine. But again, the more currently a petri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Water is ſuppoſed to paſs through the Urinal paſſages, the more danger there is of breeding the Stone. I have bound him with his own chain, to this concluſion, that <hi>Scarbrough</hi> has in it a <hi>Lapideſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent juice.</hi> They are fetters of braſs, he can never break them aſunder.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He added</hi> (pag. 38.) <hi>a particular mans experience of ſuch an one, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially as my ſelf may be Fallacious.</hi> He miſtakes, the Experiment I made of the Water, was the foundation<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of my Poſition, my particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar experience did but confirm it; therefore, I ſay, an Experiment agreeing with the Experience, not of one, but of many, cannot be Fallacious: he heard me (<hi>p.</hi> 35.) proteſting to the world, both as to my ſelf, Patients, and Relations it was ſo.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:59064:39"/>
            <p>I ſhall now be more particular to convince him and others, that it was not my experience <hi>only,</hi> that <hi>Scarbrough Spaw</hi> is bad for the Stone.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>William Beckwith</hi> never had any ſymptom of Gravel, until he uſed <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Water, which he obſerved, did give him Fits of Stone, and therefore he gave it over, and ſince betook himſelf for <hi>Knaisbrough.</hi> Mr. <hi>John Aton</hi> came to <hi>Scarbrough</hi> by mine advice, he did commend the Water for its purging property, but it gave him a touch of his old diſtemper the Stone, of which he was cured per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly at <hi>London</hi> fifteen years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and never from that time, till he drunk <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> had he the leaſt remembrance of it; this did ſo affright him, that he durſt not drink any more of theſe Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:59064:39"/>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>Johnſon</hi> of <hi>Kibleſworth,</hi> came to <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> by mine advice, for prevention of the Fits of Gravel, ſhe uſed ſometime to be afflicted with; after her return from thence, ſhe had her Fits more frequently, and more violently; beſides, as the Water dealt with me, ſo did it with this Gentlewoman. No ſooner did the Stone paſs out of one Kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney into the Bladder, but imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ſhe felt from the other Kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, a darting pain ſtrike into her great Toe, which made her halt for a fortnight after. She never in all her life time, had any fit of the Gout before, or ſince ſhe left off drinking of <hi>Scarbrough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall but add one other inſtance expreſſed in a Letter to me, which I judge is as a remarkable one againſt <hi>Scarbrough Spaw,</hi> as that of Mr. <hi>Waugh,</hi> to <hi>Dr. Witty,</hi> cited, (<hi>p.</hi> 60.) is for it.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:59064:40"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Wilmer</hi> of <hi>Bow,</hi> near <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> being afflicted with the Stone, comes to <hi>Scarbrough</hi> in (70.) to drink the Water; his Wife (being with him) was pleaſed to drink of it alſo for company, though ſhe was never ſubject to the Diſeaſe in the leaſt; after ſhe had drunk it two or three weeks, they both return to <hi>York,</hi> and within two days, ſhe fell into ſuch a violent fit of the Colick and Stone (with almoſt a total ſuppreſſion of Urine) that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hours ſhe almoſt diſpaired of life; but by the uſe of good reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, ſhe voided a good quantity of Sand of Gravel; ſome bits as big as great pins heads, and wondred at ſuch a ſurpriſal; for ſhe ſaid, ſhe never had a fit of Stone before, in all her life, and thought the Spaw wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter had bred it; well, after ſome weeks recovery, ſhe went up to <hi>London,</hi> and then ſhe had another
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:59064:40"/>dangerous fit of the Stone again, which had like to have coſt her life, but by the help of two Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians there, ſhe got quit of two or three Stones; one of which was as big as an ordinary Almond, which ſtill confirmed her belief, that the <hi>Spaw</hi> had made them; well, the next year (71.) ſhe came again with her Husband to <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> and brought thoſe ſtones to ſhew <hi>Doctor Witty,</hi> reſolving not to drink any more, unleſs the <hi>Doctor</hi> gave aſſurance the Spaw had not occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned them. Being over-per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by the <hi>Doctor</hi> to drink a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, in a few days tryal, ſhe fell the third time into ſuch a deſperate fit of it, for ſeveral days, that her Husband and Children, bemoaning her, thought verily ſhe would have ended her days there; this I was an eye-witneſs of, as to the firſt part; the reſt was a relation to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59064:41"/>me from her own Mouth this laſt Summer. <hi>Henry Wilkinſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He is proving (<hi>pag.</hi> 39.) that <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> cannot breed the ſtone, becauſe it expells them. That it expells them, it was confeſſed, but the inference denied in the place before cited.</p>
            <p>He argues, <hi>Scarbrough cannot be either the material, or efficient cauſe of breeding ſtone; not the material cauſe of ſtone, becauſe that muſt be Craſs matter, but the Spaw is a pure water;</hi> ergo.</p>
            <p>As pure as it looks, if all the Sand and Clay in it, were put in his eyes, he would then ſee
'tis otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>But for him to affirm that Craſs matter, is the material cauſe of ſtone, is no leſs than a groſs miſtake. Spirit of Urine, mixt with pure Spirit of Wine, they both do coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate together into a firm Salt: Fermented Urine diſtilled, before
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:59064:41"/>half be cummed over, there is found all about the ſides of the receiver, a Sabulous matter: <hi>Sat namque conſtat,</hi> ſays <hi>Helmont, delithiaſi,</hi> (p. 683.) <hi>quod in lotio humano (eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ſanorum) ſemper ſit proxima materia inviſibilis, &amp; ſemen ad duelech.</hi> But if <hi>Doctor Witty</hi> be willing to learn, and can underſtand <hi>Helmont</hi> well, he may be informed by that Author, how ſtones are bred in our Bodies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi Spiritus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rinae invenit vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile non coagulatum coagulabile ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men (quia terreae indolis) ſuum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerens coagulum, conſtringit ean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem aporrhaeam in terram; conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> viribus utrimque, fit nova cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atura, quae eſt nativitas duelech,</hi> Helmont. (p. 687.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The efficient cauſe of ſtone it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be, becauſe it is cooling,</hi> for ſays he, <hi>Thus the ſtones are bred, the fiery heat of the Reins, and circumjacent
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59064:42"/>parts, condueeth ſome Craſs matter into Gravel and Stone; even as Potters Clay is by heat, hardned into a ſtone.</hi> Who will blot Paper to tell him how <hi>Helmont</hi> has confuted this irrational opinion, which is contrary to the judgment of <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates, Sennertus,</hi> and with him all Modern Authors, that has not put their Thumbs under <hi>Galens Girdle;</hi> yea, contrary to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of all afflicted with that diſtemper; who can feel that Stone and Gravel cauſeth the heat in the Reins, and circumjacent parts, and not the heat of them cauſeth the Stone; in as much as they find, if ever the petrifying Spirit be extinct and gone, they are never more trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with any preternatural heat in thoſe parts, than others that know not what fits of Stone meant.</p>
            <p>If heat were the cauſe, <hi>ſine quâ non,</hi> of Gravel and Stone in the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59064:42"/>Kidneys; how eaſily were it, by the Galenical method, to prevent it for ever; a little <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ng. Populeon,</hi> or <hi>refrigerous Galeni,</hi> would do the feat. I would know of him, how it comes to paſs, that there are great ſtones bred in the Bladder ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently; ſuppoſe heat were there, as much as in a Potters Furnace, it could not harden Craſs matter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſtone there; becauſe the water continually coming thither, would keep it moiſt. Again, how could ſtones be bred by heat in the hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of the Lungs, as in Mr. <hi>Procters</hi> caſe, which continually ſucks in cooling Air. How comes it to paſs that old men, <hi>quatenus,</hi> ſuch are more ſubject to ſtone, than others of middle age. Thou ſeeſt that <hi>Dr. W.</hi> in his deſcription of the ſtone, is of the queſtion both as to matter and form.</p>
            <p>But ſays he, <hi>Our Author accuſeth it as a material cauſe.</hi> I accuſe <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:59064:43"/>to breed the ſtone, both as a material and efficient cauſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He goes on, perhaps, I might be beguiled in taking up Sand with the Water, which made me look upon it as an inſeparable adjunct of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> What a weariſomneſs is it, to anſwer ſuch trifling words? why did did not the Diſſector, before he fell on his work, try the water by boyling it? and then if he did not find a great deal of gretty ſtone powder at the bottom of the Veſſel, he might have put his Whittle to my throat, and ſaid to me, <hi>Tonſtall</hi> thou lyeſt; perhaps, indeed, he did try it, <hi>but we hear not a word of that.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he further urgeth, (p. 42.) <hi>All Mineral Waters will let fall ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the bottom, called Ochre; yet Learned Writers, on the ſubject, never thought the worſe of them.</hi> I know Allom waters will let fall its
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:59064:43"/>Glebe, as Vitrioline do their Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cothar, neither do I think the worſe of them for it. The <hi>Spaw</hi> at <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> does ſo, which is an <hi>Allom</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. If <hi>Scarbrough</hi> were as inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent as this, <hi>Doctor Witty,</hi> and I, ſhould ſoon agree together. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and publiſh, that I have Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimented this Water, as I did that at <hi>Scarbrough;</hi> and it lets fall no gretty ſtone powder to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom: Hereby <hi>Doctor Witty</hi> is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confuted in two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That I picked a quarrel with <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> only for by-ends, and out of a mean deſign, to draw Patients from thence to <hi>Knaiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough.</hi> If I had been ſo baſely Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited, I would not have told him thus much of <hi>Malton,</hi> which he confeſſes (<hi>p.</hi> 201. firſt Edition) <hi>To be of like vertue, and in operation, as quick and ſtrong, as that at</hi> Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough. Here let him ſet up, and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:59064:44"/>if he can bring the Patients from <hi>Knaisbrough,</hi> to him thither, I ſhall not complain.</p>
            <p>Secondly, He is confuted by this alſo, that it is a peculiar fault in <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> as it is a petrifying wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, not as an Allom water, that it caſts a gretty ſtone powder to the bottom in the boyling.</p>
            <p>Yet another evaſion. <hi>Doctor Witty</hi> relates, a notable Experiment <hi>ſhown before ſeveral perſons of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> I wonder, I met not with it in his Letter at large to the <hi>R. S. Two quarts of</hi> Spaw <hi>water, paſſeth through the filter, whilſt it is cold, cleaverly, leaving not a grain of Sand behind;</hi> and thence he <hi>infers, that if they drink the water unwarm'd, it will, he doubts not, paſs through the Body as eaſily, leaving no dregs behind, as it did in the filter.</hi> I'le ſet ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Experiment againſt this, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve Pearl (prepared with Sp. of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:59064:44"/>
               <hi>Venus</hi>) in ſpringing water, filter it, and it ſhall go all through, not leaving a grain behind. Were it true, therefore, that this Pearl-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, would ſo paſs through the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as it did the filter, then ſave but the Ladies water that drank it, and we may find the Pearl again, and that an hundred times over. If <hi>Swelfer</hi> were alive, he ſhould thank <hi>Doctor Witty,</hi> who by this Experiment would prove, that his <hi>Spir. veneris,</hi> is <hi>tantum non,</hi> the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor <hi>Alkaheſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He endeavours, again, to put by the force of this Argument, by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming, (<hi>pag.</hi> 43.) <hi>Though the fire make a ſeparation of the groſs parts of the water, from the pure, yet the natural heat in the Bowels doth not ſo when we drink it;</hi> but the water paſſeth through the body, as pure as we put it into our mouths: His firſt proof is, a moſt impertinent
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:59064:45"/>inſtance, of the <hi>blood which is flued in our veins, yet exhaled on the fire, it will be thick like Starch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let <hi>Doctor Witty,</hi> who is a Maſter of Secrets (yet will tell me none) take the liquor <hi>Alkaheſt,</hi> and firſt digeſt the blood with it, then ſet it on the fire, and he will ſee that all the blood will be exhaled, and no thick matter left behind.</p>
            <p>He conſiders not, that the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent parts of our body, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with divers Functions;
'tis the faculty of the veins and arteries <hi>(quam diu cuſtodes bene ſe habent)</hi> to circulate the blood, which alſo evaporates through the pores, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſeparation of any Sediment, or <hi>caput mortuum,</hi> becauſe of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural <hi>Alkahest</hi> that recides there; 'tis the faculty of the bowels, by the Ferments there, to make ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration betwixt pure and impure, and to leave a Sediment, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:59064:45"/>
               <hi>caput mortuum,</hi> to be caſt forth as an Excrement.</p>
            <p>His ſecond inſtance, like the former is, <hi>That Sack put on a hot fire-ſhovel, will leave a white Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but paſſes well through our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</hi> In Sack there is a Volatile Sulphur and Salt, duly contempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, which makes it ſo great a Cordial: Being caſt on the Fire, theſe two Principles ſuddenly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends each other, and unites in, <hi>aliquid tertium,</hi> like Starch. Yet let him take the Tartar of Wine, which is the groſſeſt part of it, and Volatilize it, as he is told in <hi>Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cetan de medecin. priſc. Philoſ. cap.</hi> 6. And then put it upon a hot fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhovel, and it ſhall all evaporate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſmoke, and leave nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind; ſo that his two inſtances ſerve nothing to his purpoſe, to ſhew the different effects betwixt the heat of the Fire, and of our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:59064:46"/>but rather the difference of Functions, betwixt that in the Veins, and that in the Bowels; and the difference of Concretes, how ſome are volatile, and ſome are not. But if <hi>Doctor Witty</hi> would make <hi>Scarbrough Spaw</hi> as parallel to Sack, as I have made it to the Dropping Well at <hi>Knaisbrough,</hi> we will all come and drink with him.</p>
            <p>But what needs all this trouble of Experiments? <hi>Doctor Witty</hi> hits the nail on the head, and drives it home at one blow; ſays he (<hi>p.</hi> 44.) <hi>A petrifying water is an excellent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy againſt the Stone.</hi> Alas, poor <hi>Galen,</hi> Doctor <hi>Witty,</hi> has broken thine head at this one ſtroke; a word and a blow with him, will confute us both: remember what he ſaid before of <hi>Galen;</hi> and is not this in him, <hi>crimen laeſae majeſtis?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:59064:46"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Contraria Contrariis curantur,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Says rational</hi> Galen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Similia Similibus curantur,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Says</hi> Doctor <hi>Witty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Welcom good Sir, I am glad to ſee you ſhake hands with <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Sic ſaevis inter ſe convenit urſis.</q>
            <p>But <hi>he has</hi> Doctor Fuller, <hi>an Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storians word for it, that a ſpring at</hi> Newenham Regis, <hi>a petrifying wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is ſound to be very ſoverain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Stone;</hi> If ſo, then 'tis the beſt expedient in the world, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the credit of <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> for him to go thither this Summer, and when he has performed his Cures there, then to bring his ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations under the hands of his <hi>Right Honourable, Right Worſhipful, Reverend,</hi> and <hi>Well-beloveds.</hi> If he will not follow mine advice, I ſhall
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:59064:47"/>be on <hi>Galens</hi> ſide, againſt <hi>Doctor Witty,</hi> for all that <hi>Fuller</hi> reports of <hi>Newenham</hi> Spring, becauſe I deſcry <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Spaw, by reaſon of the ſtone powder in it; therefore he infers, <hi>I may as well cry down Pearl, Coral, Crab-eyes, Gaſc-powder, all ſorts of Precious Stones, as dangerous againſt the Stone; and we ſhould uſe nothing, but the fiery hot Spirits of the Pſeudo-Chymiſts, if Wiſe men, and Great Ladies would believe this doctrine. N. L.</hi> doubtleſs the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſector has drunk too much of the hot, fiery Spirits of the Pſeudo-Chymiſts, which has inflamed his brain, and made him rove at this rate. What ſays Wiſe Men, and great Ladies, to this Doctrine of his? ſeeing they take Pearl and Precious Stone-powder, they may as well take the Powder ſcraped off their ſtone-walls; as if there were no difference betwixt ſtones
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:59064:47"/>in the ſtreet, and Rubies; whereas they differ, <hi>toto coelo,</hi> as we ſay, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in vertue from each other, as far as Heaven is from Earth. Hear that <hi>incomparable Philoſopher,</hi> deſcribing theſe Precious ſtones, and the common ones, <hi>Canon</hi> 172. <hi>Saxa verò &amp; lapides, quia non tam ex verâ elementorum mixtione generan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quàm ex Terra &amp; Aquae con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſu per exteriorem caloris &amp; fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goris vim, quaſi opus terreum &amp; fictile, decoquuntur; propterea om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nino stupeſcunt, à tenebrosâ frigenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que terrae &amp; aquae natura formam invalidam mutuati; de pretioſis la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillis &amp; gemmis aliter ſentiendum eſt, formas enim ſuas, à limpidiſſimus Coeli &amp; ſolis fontibus hauriunt, ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorumque corpora ſunt puriſſime roris exuberati guttulae, coeleſtibus influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiis impregnatae ac veluti concrete Coeli lacrymae, unde plurimas ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in ſe virtutes poſſident.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:59064:48"/>
            <p>As for <hi>Crab eyes and Claws,</hi> which are the Baſis of Gaſcin powder, they are noble <hi>Alkalis,</hi> ſweeting all Acidities, and therefore good for the Stone, as I ſaid before. As for <hi>Spar,</hi> it is a mark haſite of Lead, abounding with Volatile Sulphur and Salt, whereby it is very Diu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical, and therefore not only good for the Stone, as he menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but for the Dropſie alſo, which he might have found in <hi>Kirkerus,</hi> if he had read him for any other end, than to ſerve his turn in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations. If <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Water has diſſolved any one of theſe he mentions, I had been as juſt to commend it, as now in honeſty, I diſpraiſe it for the Stone.</p>
            <p>Once again he aſſaults the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, (<hi>p.</hi> 47.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>'Tis impoſſible</hi> (ſays he) <hi>for ſuch a groſs ſubſtance as Sand (which ſuppoſe we grant to be in the Water) to
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:59064:48"/>paſs through the capillar veins of the Meſentery &amp; Emulgents, which it muſt do, before it come into the Kidneys to breed the Stone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He muſt needs be quarrelſom with others, who cannot be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to himſelf; he ſaid before, (<hi>p.</hi> 43.) He did not doubt but the water, nothwithſtandiug the groſs Sediment, which the fire, as a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per inſtrument, has diſcovered to be in it, would paſs through, and penetrate our Bodies, and leave no dregs behind; now 'tis impoſſible it ſhould be ſo.</p>
            <p>Again, obſerve what he ſaid laſt, Mineral and Precious Stones, are good to expel Gravel and Stone out of the Kidneys: now he ſays, it is impoſſible they ſhould get thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, through the Capillar Veins of the Meſentery; will he alſo be againſt <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and deny, that <hi>omnis actio eſt per contactum,</hi> or
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:59064:49"/>will his Medicines kill Diſeaſes in the ſame manner (as the Gentleman told him, bragging how he had mall'd me) he had kill'd his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, namely, before he came at him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A factum eſſe ad poſſe valet argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum affirmativè;</hi> he might have read in <hi>Sennertus,</hi> that powder of Anniſeed given to a Child, for wind of the Stomach, was found in the Childs Urine next day after. I ſhall tell him of baggs of water, the skins whereof were as thick as the brim of an Hat, and before the water was drawn out of them, as big as his Head; theſe hanging upon the outward coat of the Bowels, came through into them, and was voided by ſiege. To give a reaſon how this could be (that it was ſo, I ſhall manifeſt in mine ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations) take the Anſwer of <hi>Severine,</hi> in another caſe, <hi>Quod
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:59064:49"/>manifeſtas vias corporum in his &amp; ſimilibus Atomiſtis demonſtare non poſſumus, excuſamur</hi> Hippocratis <hi>authoritate. Qui conſenſum &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirationem naturae ubique celebrat, affirmans nullam viam naturae dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficilem, omnia patere etiam per oſſa abſceſſus fieri.</hi> To confirm what <hi>Hippocrates</hi> ſays, I ſhall mention, how another vomited up, every morning, groſs purulent matter, and ſowas cleared of an Empyema, that lay above the Diaphragm, in the hollow of the Cheſt; whether by the tranſlation of the matter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Veins and Arteries, and ſo bringing it to the Stomach, or by what other ſecret ways, Nature did perform this, let the Learned diſcuſes; but that it was ſo, I ſhall evidence hereafter.</p>
            <p>A Servant of the Lord <hi>Sinklers</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> tormented with a Stone in his Kidneys, after he had
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:59064:50"/>lain about half a year, the Stone came through his Back, into the bed, leaving no wound by its paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, the man recovered.</p>
            <p>He proceeds, <hi>Nor ever was any ſuch thing (as Sand and Clay) found or ſuſpected to be in the Spaw, till this, our Author, fancied it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>More ſhame for the Diſſector to boaſt of his practice at <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> near thirty years, and all the while not to learn the skill, to ſeparate the Sand and Clay from the Salts in the Water. And is it not a prety fancy of him, to ſay of that which my hands have handled, mine eyes have ſeen, <hi>I fancyed it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another evaſion follows, <hi>But (the Sand and Clay, muſt of neceſſity be thrown by the purging property of the water into the Bowels, where no harm, nor manner of detriment can enſue, and ſo go out by ſiege.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:59064:50"/>
            <p>If the Water be drunk, it muſt of neceſſity be thrown into the Bowels, whether the Water purge, or not purge; and being there ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct by the Sand and Clay in it, both the Ductus Pancreaticus, and Cholidochus, if not, petrifie their juices; for the Faeces of the water going out by ſiege, it is but his fancy in this place; for hereafter he declares they ſtay behind, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that the water purgeth well all the while.</p>
            <p>Yet again, <hi>Nor did ever any thing happen upon the drinking of theſe waters, that could afford any the leaſt ground of jealouſie, that there was any ſuch cauſe, notwithſtanding his pretences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a loud untruth (with this aggravation upon it) contrary to his own knowledge, as will be made appear, in (<hi>p.</hi> 96.)</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:59064:51"/>
            <p>The Diſſector tired a little with his work, to divert himſelf, and the Reader, makes a Digreſſion, (<hi>p.</hi> 48.) To tell firſt of the Nature of Stone, and then of the Generation of Stones, ſays he, <hi>It is a point of no ſmall difficulty, that I am now faln upon;</hi> Fallopius <hi>his definition, he likes not,</hi> but leaves it to others to give better. <hi>But this is obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that the more pure and fine, the matter of any stone is, the harder it is;</hi> by this rule, flint is of purer matter than Pearl. So much for that Point.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the Generation of Stone is still more difficult, they are not all Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally water, becauſe they are not all pellucid, nor all of earth, for then none ſhould be pellucid; beſides, they are heavier than Earth, and yet dryer, which may not be granted. The beſt account we can give is, that every ſort of ſtone has its ſtony juice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:59064:51"/>it be Concrete, and that Concre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is furthered ſometimes by cold, and ſometimes by heat.</hi> This is the ſum of his Digreſſion. I ſhall ſay nothing to him, only a word to the Learned, and Induſtrious Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſt.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Kircher <hi>forbear thy ſighs, and wipe thine eyes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Weep not to ſee him thus Epitomize</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thy Subterranean Treaſures, ſince we ſee,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It's all the difference 'twixt him and thee.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>There are alſo ſtones generated in mens Bodies, by the immoderate heat of the parts condenſing Craſs matter,</hi> (even as Clay is hardned to a ſtone, in the Potters Furnace, ſo he ſaid before, <hi>p.</hi> 41.) For inſtance, he tells of a Stone, as hard as a Flint, which would ſtrike fire on a ſteel,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:59064:52"/>cut out of a mans Buttock, at <hi>Don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſter;</hi> you will ſay, how came the immoderate heat ſo to that part, as to condenſe Craſs matter to that extreme hardneſs? I'le tell you, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he was one of the Diſſectors ill Boys, when he taught School at <hi>Hull,</hi> and therefore got his Breech over-heated, when he was young; or elſe the man being too much delighted with paſtime, did play too long in the Winter nights, at the ſport we call hot-hand.</p>
            <p>He proceeds <hi>to a rare Spring in</hi> France, <hi>that in</hi> 24 <hi>hours time, by placing Timber, and then pumping water upon it, they may have a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Stone-bridge, made by petri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. Faber</hi> endeavouring to give a reaſon for it, he tells him, he had as good have ſaid nothing. Now hear ſomething to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, 'tis thus, <hi>The true cauſe,</hi> ſays he, <hi>muſt be this, that this whole Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:59064:52"/>that runs out of the Spring, is a Lapideſcent juice, and not water.</hi> Thus he contradicts the definition, which <hi>Kircher</hi> gives of <hi>Succus La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidificus.</hi> I demand therefore what he means by it, if it be not <hi>Saxum nitroſum aqua eliquatum;</hi> I do ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, like as he learnt from the Potter, how ſtones are bred in our bodies, ſo here he is taught by the Grape-gatherers, how theſe ſtone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridges come to paſs, <hi>viz.</hi> as the juice of Grapes runs out of the Wine-preſſes in <hi>France,</hi> ſo here <hi>the juice of Stones runs out of the Spring, which as ſoon as it ceaſes to move, immediately it hardens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus alſo the Diſſector has turned the <hi>Royal Society</hi> topſie turvy; their Art is to imitate Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; he will have Nature to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Art, both in the Potters Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, and the Wine Preſs.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:59064:53"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 54.55.56. He is deſcribing <hi>Knaisbroughs Dropping Well,</hi> for which he received ſatisfaction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>The Marginal Note, (<hi>pag.</hi> 57.) <hi>A rare caſe of help in the Stone.</hi> He mentions me, that was helped into a Fit of the Stone by drinking of it; and he is ſo fond of his Brat, a prety ſimilitude (to which I gave anſwer, (<hi>p.</hi> 34. of my Book) that he repeats it here again. The di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute was, where the Thief lurked; I ſaid in <hi>Scarbrough Spaw.</hi> The ſtone-filings I diſcovered, and by Anatomy ferreted him out. <hi>Doctor Witty</hi> was ſtudying above twelve months, how to requite me for ſo doing; his anſwer came out at laſt, the deſign whereof is to hide this Thief, if it were poſſible, from the eyes of others. A Receiver, we ſay, is worſe than a Thief; juſtly therefore was he ſet in the Pinfold;
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:59064:53"/>but ſeeing he threatens either to creep through, or over-top it, I have now bound him in a Chain, and clapt him up in cloſe Priſon. As for the Thief it ſelf, I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered it to the Judges (the Royal Society) if they will not condemn it, yet I have diſcharged the part of an honeſt man.</p>
            <p>In caſe <hi>Doctor Witty</hi> be troubled, <hi>with the over-flowing of his Gall</hi> at this, let me diſſwade him from drinking any more <hi>Scarbrough</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for it is very bad for the Jaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice.</p>
            <p>He proceeds (<hi>p.</hi> 59.) againſt my fourth Argument, endeavouring to overthrow it by contrary inſtances; he produceth one I know not, the other I do, Mr. <hi>George Waugh,</hi> who continues ſtill with bad Fits of the Stone; <hi>but we have not a word of this.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:59064:54"/>
            <p>
               <hi>He thinks fit,</hi> (p. 61.) <hi>to inſert a ſtory,</hi> as old as <hi>Pauls,</hi> however I thank him for his good will; ſorry he is, that I ſhould come under the knife again, and be cut for the Stone; therefore he will teach me a cure <hi>from the caſualty of the knife halft, lying upon the Radiſh root, which being made of a Stone taken out of the Bladder, melted away conſiderably.</hi> His inference upon this that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Radiſh, <hi>Helmont</hi> has pull'd up by the roots, ſhewing how the power of ſuch vegetable diſſolvents is enervated, before they come where the Stone is, by the ferments of concoction.</p>
            <p>(<hi>Pag.</hi> 63.64.) He mentions Mr. <hi>Proctors</hi> caſe I ſpoke of, and Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſeth <hi>Doctor Neale,</hi> that did ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe him to <hi>Knaisbrough,</hi> to whom I refer the Diſſector.</p>
            <p>He gave out before, that I placed the petrifying property of <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough,</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:59064:54"/>in <hi>Nitre,</hi> and manfully beat the Air about it; now he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands me better, <hi>'tis in the ſtone perticles,</hi> ſaith he (<hi>p.</hi> 64.) But how come theſe to be found in <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough? Thus, the fire in the boyling of the water, does condenſe ſome fixed parts of the Minerals, and Metalline ſubſtances</hi> (even ſo ſaid the Parſon, that <hi>Tenderden</hi> Steeple was the cauſe of <hi>Goodwin Sands</hi>) <hi>however, yet exceeding ſhort of that proportion that he mentions.</hi> I wonder he ſhould ſay ſo, what need of extenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating the matter thus? if it be not plain Sand, but only the Mineral and Metalline Subſtances, what worſe is <hi>Scarbrough</hi>'s water for them? though they were exceeding above the proportion, that I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned; nor indeed, is it worth the enquiring; what is his Book worth then, which he entitles an Anſwer? Surely not the Reading. For if he
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:59064:55"/>have not enquired into mine Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment, of <hi>Scarbrough Spaw,</hi> and upon tryal found, that 'tis falſe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as to the thing, or to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of it, his whole diſcourſe is impertinent, as indeed it is, ſave only, that it ſerves to illuſtrate what I have ſaid of <hi>Scarbrough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obſerve now his pitiful ſhufflings, to make the Sand, found in <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough,</hi> an innocent thing, and but that which is common to all wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            <p>His firſt Argument.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Boyle,</hi> in his Ninth Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (<hi>p.</hi> 390.) ſays, that diſtilled Rain-water, left at the bottom a fine white Earth; the Diſſector, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his wonted manner of dealing, with all Chymical Authors, abuſes this noble perſon, reporting of him, <hi>That he ſound there a quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Sand, as a bottom Sediment.</hi> His ſecond Argument, would throw
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:59064:55"/>Sand and Clay that is in <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> into all the <hi>Spaws</hi> in <hi>Europe;</hi> ſuch, ſays he, there is in <hi>Burbon Spaw;</hi> his proof for it is, the <hi>Lord Faulcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi> ſhewed him the Minerals of it; his Lordſhip told me, they were pure Mineral Salts, extracted out of the Spaw; he goes on, <hi>Epſam, Tanbridge, Barnett, has the like</hi> Sandy Sediment. If this charge of his be not true, then let the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians, who attend at thoſe Waters, return the Diſſector the thanks he deſerves for reproaching them. If it be true, let them give me better reaſons than he has done, why they are not petrifying, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they have diſſolved ſtones. <hi>Knaisbrough water, upon my own knowledge, ſays he, after evaporation, yields a great proportion of Sand and Clay.</hi> I diſtilled a quart of it laſt year, and there was not one grain of Sand at the bottom, only ten
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:59064:56"/>grains of a Colcothar, which I have to ſhew; yea, <hi>Doctor French,</hi> ſaith he, (<hi>p.</hi> 66.) <hi>in his Book of</hi> Knais<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough, <hi>confeſſeth it;</hi> his words are theſe, The water being evaporated, leaves behind it an inſipid powder, of a darkiſh colour, like unto which powder, will that blewiſh cream, or skin, which ſwims upon the ſaid water after long ſtanding be, when it is dryed <hi>French, p.</hi> 69. what prety Hocus Pocus tricks are here? every Spaw after evapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, has its proper Sediment, ſuitable to the Minerals it has diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved. <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Sediment is Sandy, becauſe it has diſſolved Stone: The Diſſector by the Art of <hi>Legerdimain,</hi> would make all the Sediments of Spaws, whatſoever, to appear the very ſame with <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough,</hi> when no waters in the world has the like, except thoſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that are petrifying.</p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:59064:56"/>
            <p>He cites <hi>Faber,</hi> who ſpeaks in words to the ſame purpoſe, as <hi>Dr. French</hi> ſaid before, which is true of all <hi>Vitrioline</hi> waters; but it ſeems any inſpid Earth or Ochre, is Sand with <hi>Doctor Witty,</hi> he makes no difference.</p>
            <p>I found by Experiment, that <hi>Scarbrough</hi> has a Sandy Sediment, and therefore to return upon the Diſſector his own words, (<hi>p.</hi> 67.) <hi>Either he did not know this, when he writ his Book of</hi> Scarbrough, <hi>or he did; If he had not known it, then it betokens ignorance in that part of Philoſophy, wherein he ought, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, to have been better inſtructed; if he did know it, and yet goes about to buzze it into the heads of the vulgar,</hi> That <hi>Scarbrough</hi> water has no other Faeces, than inſipid Earth, common to all waters, it <hi>ſavours still worſe,</hi> as coming from the Crackfart of <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Spaw.</p>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:59064:57"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 68. to 72. He frisks it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, as if he were making a third Edition of <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> declaring, that it ſharpens the Apetite, <hi>making them eat like Farmers;</hi> it has been better expreſt, like Seamen, for doubtleſs, the Sea air is a good whetſtone to it, as any that walks near it on the Sands, will find, though they drink no Water; but why doth he apply this as an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to me? ſhow where I quarrel with <hi>Scarbrough</hi> upon this account. To what I ſaid, (<hi>pag.</hi> 27.) of the Sand and Clay in <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> cleaving to the Bowels, <hi>Dr. Simpſon</hi> is put upon theſe remedies and cautions, to prevent the miſchief thereof. Firſt, He preſcribes a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trioline Vomit, which doth ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the ſtone of the Bowels; the Relaxation whereof renders them ſuſceptible of a ſtony Incruſtation, from the Sabulum of the water,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:59064:57"/>whereby they become the cauſe of all thoſe Diſeaſes that happen by drinking the Water.</p>
            <p>Secondly, He prohibits immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate exerciſe, and too ſoon eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after the Water, leſt the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tex, wherein the Sabulous matter is diſſolved, be thereby in danger to be carried by the Thoracical Veſſels, into the fourth digeſtion of the Heart, and thence into the habit of the body, whereby it may lay a foundation for the <hi>Gout, Stone, Scurvy, Feaver,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, After the two or three days drinking Water, he adviſeth Purging Pills, and to reſt a day or two after, from taking the Spaw Water; and that to prevent a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den precipitation of the ſtrong matter, upon the Panicles of the Inteſtines, after their abſtertion or cleanſing by the former Solutine. When all this is ſaid and done, he is
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:59064:58"/>is ſaid and done, he is not peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory in his dictates, but concludes, if any, who are inclined to the Stone and Gout, be jealous of drinking the Water, in caſe his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed method do not ſatisfie, then he commends the Eſſence of <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Spaw, which is a Salt depurated from all the Stony Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretions that are in the water. Theſe he ſuppoſeth will become powerful againſt all thoſe Diſeaſes, whoſe Seminaries conſiſt in a Sabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous petrifying property, as the Stone, Gout, Jaundice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Diſſector likes not ſuch plain and honeſt dealing, and therefore, he ſays, <hi>Dr. Simpſons Anſwer, in the Judgment of Learned men (ſuch as himſelf) deſerves nothing, but to be imployed in the most homely uſes.</hi> You may gather what he means by it, ſaving your preſence; well, <hi>If any anſwer be but like that, I have
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:59064:58"/>loſt my labour; Parturiunt montes,</hi> I ſhall bring forth his reply, 'tis this (p. 73.) <hi>Hard words indeed, enough to fright Children; but they that are wiſe, will not be ſtartled with Bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bears; the cauſe, and the effect, are much alike; the truth is, 'tis n othing more than a frivolous conceit, and not worthy to be replyed to.</hi> To be homely with him, I judge an Oy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter woman at <hi>Billingsgate,</hi> will give as ſatisfactory an anſwer as this.</p>
            <p>The Reſty Jadiſh Fit that <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough</hi> Spaw takes after ſometimes drinking, I demanded, (<hi>p.</hi> 25.) If it were the manner of other waters to do ſo? he Anſwers, <hi>Yes, I can tell him, that</hi> Knaisbrough <hi>water, will not go through, at any time, in ordinary bodies, unleſs it be drawn, or driven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Suppoſe this calumny were true, what is it to the purpoſe? <hi>Knaiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough</hi>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:59064:59"/>purgeth by Urine, as all Vitrioline Waters do; and this it doth effect ſo long, as any pleaſe to drink on't. How can the Diſſector then charge it, with a Reſty Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Fit? when was it obſerved, that after it had wrought well this way with any, it afterwards ſtop'd, and would not paſs by Urine, but ſwell the Belly, and bring upon the Patient ſuch Evils, which the Diſſector himſelf acknowledgeth <hi>Scarbrough</hi> will do. See then this impertinent Tattle, yet thus he boaſteth, <hi>I am certain no water in the world, that I read of, is leſs guilty of this Reſty Fit, than</hi> Scarbrough; for proof he cites <hi>Dr. Heer, of the</hi> Germane Spaw, <hi>confeſſing that thoſe that drink it, have ſcarce one ſtool in ſix days, even ſuch as were wont to retriograde once every day at home.</hi> Doth not theſe <hi>words, and the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for which he cites them, agree as
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:59064:59"/>an Harp, and an Harrow? Heer</hi> gives the reaſon whereof, <hi>Humoribus aquarum vi ad renes &amp; veſicam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latis ſicci ora fieri inteſtina, atque alvum inde pigreſcere neceſſarium eſt,</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 138.) This is the Diſſectors reaſoning <hi>Knaisbrough,</hi> and the <hi>German Spaw</hi> purgeth by Urine, and not by ſtool; therefore they are more to be blamed, for taking a Reſty Jadiſh Fit, than <hi>Scarbrough</hi> is. The account why <hi>Scarbrough</hi> alone is guilty of this, amongſt all the Spaws in the world in uſe, (that I read of) is, 'tis both a purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and a petrifying Water; the purging property, takes effect pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, and proceeds on regularly, until the petrifying property pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, and then all the water ſtops, which of neceſſity it muſt do, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dam'd up with Sand and Clay; which the water left behind in the Bowels, after ſo long a time drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:59064:60"/>Of like inſignificancy is his parallel of Diet-drinks, which as ſoon as they have purged away that, for which they were given, are of no further uſe. The inſtance I gave for this Reſty Jadiſh Fit of <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> the Diſſector gives this Anſwer (<hi>p.</hi> 750.) <hi>As for the Lord he mentions, I know whom he means, that Lord told me, he could never get quit of him, till at length he yielded to take ſomething of him.</hi> That the Reader may be aſſured once for all, that the Diſſectors whole diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is fraught, as full of untruths, as 'tis of impertinencies, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſtories; let this inſtance bear witneſs, the Lord <hi>Pawlet,</hi> Brother to the <hi>Marqueſs</hi> of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> made his complaint to me, as I mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, (<hi>p.</hi> 25. of my Book) I knew the cauſe was from the dirty Faeces of the Spaw that laid in his Bowels, and therefore the Eſſence I judged
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:59064:60"/>moſt proper for him, becauſe it is a Salt that was ſeparated from the Sand and Clay, and would up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that account, eaſily joyn with thoſe in his Bowels, to cleanſe them off, with which they were once united in the water. The ground of this apprehenſion is both agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Atomical Philoſophy, in reſpect of the ſutableneſs of their Textures, and to all Experiments of Chymiſtry.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Lordſhip</hi> being ſatisfied with the reaſon I gave, deſired to take it, and therefore I went with him under the Penthouſe, and in the preſence of the Diſſector, put it to his Spaw-water, which made the Diſſector to grumble, ſaying, <hi>There was nothing in that eſſence, but Allom and Nitre.</hi> I ſmill'd to hear him commend it in thoſe words, which he uttered, to make his Lordſhip undervalue it. There is nothing
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:59064:61"/>more in the Spaw, but Allom and Nitre, except Sand and Clay, and that is the excellency of the eſſence that 'tis well quit of them.</p>
            <p>That afternoon his Lordſhip ſent his Servant to deſire my company, when I came, he gave me thanks, and told me, he believed, he had purged that day, all the water he had drunk in three or four days before; which lay ſo heavy upon him, that he was ſick, and ill at eaſe with it. I neither asked, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a Farthing of his Lordſhip; I have therefore mentioned his name, that if he be alive, he may do me right; his Honour is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned to acquit me of the Diſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors opprobrious aſperſion; I hate to be an <hi>Interloper.</hi> Such is the manner of ſome Phyſitians, that one cannot come near them, but they will cleave like a Bur, which <hi>you cannot get quite off,</hi> without
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:59064:61"/>pulling ſome wool off the back; ſuch are <hi>Mendicants,</hi> more than Mendicants, they'l Lackquay it up and down, proffering their ſervice, where 'tis neither needed nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired.</p>
            <p>Such low deſigns I leave to the <hi>Diſſector,</hi> whom I obſerved to be too nimble for the <hi>Drummer</hi> of <hi>Scarbrough;</hi> though he, poor man, made all the haſte he could, to bid their Worſhips welcom to the Spaw.</p>
            <q>Turpe est doctori cum culpa redarguit ipſum.</q>
            <p>He complains (p. 76.) <hi>That of all the Authors, who have given rules for drinking Spaw-waters, none ever met with ſuch contradiction, and wreſting of their ſenſe, as he has from me;</hi> this reaſon, for his ſevere charge is; <hi>I make another uſe of his rule,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:59064:62"/>than he intended it;</hi> for 'tis granted, he ſhewed more honeſty then wit, therefore, to mention it; his rule is, (<hi>p.</hi> 211. <hi>ſecond Edition) When ſuch, and ſuch Evils come upon the Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Water, then it is high time wholly for them to deſiſt.</hi> I enquired into the ground of this rule, and it could be no other, than his own obſervation. Experience had taught him, that though for ſome time, his Patients found benefit by the Waters, yet by longer continuance of drinking, they found ſuch harms, which put him upon giving his Rule: This evil (it may be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed) he did not ſo much as ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to be in the Water; I told him it was, and that from the Stone and Clay Faeces that was in it; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in now, am I blame worthy for this? nay, I'le ſay more, he mentions <hi>Dr. Heer, Dr. Dean, Dr. French, Dr. Rooſly,</hi> giving their Rules for
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:59064:62"/>drinking water; let him ſhew me, amongſt theſe Authors, any ſuch Rule, as this of his, which I have taken notice of, and I will cry <hi>pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cavi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He wonders</hi> (p. 77.) <hi>that I ſhould call the Salts, extracted out of the Spaw, an offence, thereby excluding the groſſer parts (Sand and Clay) which are in the Water from being Eſſential to it, any more than the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which is of a groſſer ſubſtance than the Soul, ſhould be excluded from being the eſſential part of man.</hi> I wonder, alſo, why the Diſſector ſhould thus plead, to have theſe dirty Faeces eſſential to the Spaw; but I'le remove this Mountain, that he may no longer marvel at it. Impurities of any mixt body, are not eſſential to it; they ſupervened upon the earth, when it was curſed for ſin, and are by Art, as a natural effect, in ſome good meaſure ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:59064:63"/>from it; therefore we call that the Eſſence of a thing, which contains the whole Craſis of the ſubject matter, nothing wanting there from, but its impurities, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly termed a <hi>caput mortuum.</hi> If the body be nothing elſe, but a <hi>caput mortuum,</hi> to a man, it might then be accounted no eſſential part of him, <hi>moſt likely the Diſſectors up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per parts, give only a—</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He argues again, <hi>If the Salt be the only Eſſence, then it will follow, that</hi> Knaisbrough <hi>water has little or no Eſſence, becauſe it has little or no Salt in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Even ſo do blind men judge of Colours, as if what is the Eſſence of the one Spaw, ſuppoſe <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough,</hi> muſt be the Eſſence of the other at <hi>Knaisbrough,</hi> or elſe it has none. Salts extracted, are the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence only of Saline Waters; ſuch are <hi>Scarbrough, Sulph.</hi> well, and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:59064:63"/>
               <hi>Burbon,</hi> the Eſſence whereof, the Lord <hi>Faulconbridge</hi> ſhow'd to the <hi>Diſſector.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſays he (<hi>p.</hi> 78.) <hi>The Volatile Spirits are Eſſential to all ſorts of Spaw-waters, and if it were not for theſe,</hi> Knaisbrough <hi>Spaw were not worth a ruſh.</hi> He has more confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, than skill of Spaw-waters, to ſay ſo: He confeſſeth in his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>Doctor Foot,</hi> Printed in the Tranſlations of the <hi>Royal Society,</hi> that he could not meet with <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chenius;</hi> it ſeems he is at the ſame loſs ſtill, which makes him ſo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory. The Generality of Spaws are Acid Waters. Acid Spirits, we know by experience, are not ſo Volatile, as to loſe the leaſt of their vertues, by ſtanding open in the Air, though for a long time; but the Spaws, that are Acid Waters, do loſe their vertue, in a few days, out of the Fountain, though never
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:59064:64"/>ſo cloſe ſtopped up in Bottles; we may therefore neceſſarily infer from hence, that it is not from the Vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tility of their Spirits, that their vertue is ſo ſoon vaniſhed and gone, but from another moſt rational ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt; for which I refer him to the Author he has not ſeen. The worth and excellency of <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Spaw is, that an <hi>Embrionate Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur, has corroded Iron in it,</hi> which makes it Stomachical, Deopilative, Diuretical, and ſtrengthning all the noble parts. A fig for the <hi>Diſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors</hi> Volatile Spirits here, they are not worth a ruſh.</p>
            <p>He doth ſtill perſiſt (<hi>p.</hi> 79.) in perſwading us to put forth our eyes, and blindly to believe him, that the Sediment which we ſee to be Sand and Clay, is <hi>nothing elſe than the fixed parts of Minerals or Metals, which the fire condenceth, and that theſe are of a ſingular uſe
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:59064:64"/>to the fortifying of the Natural parts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fire condenceth the Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, by exhaling the water, ſo far from them, that they ſettle into Chryſtals, which, nevertheleſs, will diſſolve again in Water, and paſs all through the filter, not leaving the leaſt atom behind; if theſe Fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces then be, what he ſays they are, why will not they paſs the filter? which he confeſſes will not. Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals then they are not; for Metals, he tells us of none in <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> but Iron. If that were it, why did he not, when he preſented his ſeven or eight Extracts to the <hi>R. S.</hi> tell them this is Iron, and if they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd on't, I ſhould have yielded to him, that there is Vitriol in <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough</hi> Spaw; however, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they be, he ſays of them, that <hi>they fortifie the Natural parts.</hi> I gather from hence, that the Diſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor is of the <hi>Carteſian</hi> Sect, taking
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:59064:65"/>the body of man for a fine En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, and therefore he, as a cunning Engineer, will fortifie the parts with Sand and Clay, by the help of the Potters Furnace, making a Bull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work about them, impregnable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the ſtorms and batteries of preternatural Diſeaſes. The Lord <hi>Er.</hi> caſe which I mention, (<hi>p.</hi> 57.) <hi>He confeſſes</hi> (p. 80.) <hi>frets him more, than all my Book beſide.</hi> I wiſh him more patience for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; He refers to (<hi>p.</hi> 149. <hi>Edit.</hi> 2.) here he is mounted into <hi>Helmonts</hi> Aenigmatical Chariot, <hi>glances, dark language,</hi> being of the ſame mind with him, <hi>not to have his meaning publickly known.</hi> I proteſt, <hi>in verbo Medici,</hi> 'tis an untruth, like the reſt of his ſtories, to ſay, that <hi>I asked him again, and again, with very much importunity, whoſe caſe it was.</hi> My light burns dim; oh for a pair of <hi>Galenical Snuffers!</hi> the old
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:59064:65"/>man <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> his <hi>Spectacles,</hi> cannot help me to read; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>What? pump me, and then tell abroad my Secret?</hi> I declare, he does me wrong, for I was never guilty of ſo much folly yet, as to pump for Wine out of a <hi>dry Hoggshead.</hi> But that I may give the Reader ſatisfaction, I ſhall give a true account of this matter. Whilſt I was at <hi>Knaisbrough,</hi> the report came, that the <hi>Lord Er.</hi> went to <hi>Scarbrough</hi> to drink the Waters, and came home in the Jaundice, of which he ſhortly dyed. I ſaid then to <hi>Dr. Neale</hi> (who was with me when this news was told) that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, <hi>Scarbrough</hi> water had ſome miſchievous thing in it, for it was never heard of before, that any ſhould take the Jaundice, which is founded on Obſtructions, by drinking Spaw-waters that are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obſtructive. This ſcruple againſt
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:59064:66"/>
               <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> I carried with me thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and therefore the firſt time of my coming, I asked the <hi>Diſſector</hi> how it came to paſs, that the <hi>Lord Er.</hi> got the Jaundice, by drinking of the Water? he gave me the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer I mentioned in my Book. This is the truth, and the whole truth; I appeal then to the Reader, how I have deſerved ſuch language from him, as <hi>I did unworthily, the very School-boys will blame me for this. This is not done like a Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, but</hi> you may underſtand like Knave and Raſcal, by that long ſcratch.</p>
            <p>It ſeems, <hi>Secundae cogitationes ſunt meliores,</hi> he is now provided of a better anſwer, than he gave me at the firſt; <hi>Nor had the</hi> Lord Er. <hi>any Jaundice, but a Cachexy which he brought with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He comes now (<hi>p.</hi> 83.) to the Aldermans caſe I mentioned, (<hi>p.</hi> 40.)
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:59064:66"/>His poſition is, <hi>That no man can call a Diſeaſe the Jaundice, if it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear not in the skin.</hi> This he would prove from the definition <hi>Galen</hi> makes of the <hi>Jaundice, to whom, he ſays, agrees all the Princes of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick;</hi> yea, that <hi>Hippocrates and Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont, they will let me ſee, the Jaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice is not to be judged, without it do appear in the skin.</hi> I ſaid in the entrance of this Book, that the Diſſector wanted one eye; by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the thick darkneſs that is continually in his Library (if he have any) he could not ſee the light of Chymiſtry, how Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſplendently it doth brighten the Art of Phyſick; he now gives evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence againſt himſelf, that he is a <hi>Monoculous</hi> upon a worſe account; he wants the eye of reaſon, and will therefore judge diſeaſes only by the eye of ſence. And becauſe he reigned a Monarch, at <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough,</hi>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:59064:67"/>thirty years, perſwades him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Regali more,</hi> that all other Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians will wink of one eye at him, for faſhion ſake. If this that he hath ſaid of the Jaundice, be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, thence it will follow, that the Small Pox, which is a Diſeaſe that diffuſeth through the whole body, into the skin, cannot be called, or judged to be what it is, till it make its appearance to the view of all the beholders. In this caſe, good Ladies, you muſt not ſend for the Diſſector, when your Children are very ſick, to ask him what they ail. Now, becauſe he will not allow me to ſay I ſuſpected, but brands it <hi>with a new way of diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very,</hi> and will make it alone, as if I had ſaid, <hi>I ſancied it.</hi> I ſhall here relate a ſad ſtory, how Eminent Phyſitians miſcarried only, becauſe they did <hi>not ſuſpect</hi> My much Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Friend, a Baronet in <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:59064:67"/>ſent his Eldeſt Son to the Inns of Court; being there, he falls ſick, the Learned Doctors treated him as in a Fever, with cooling Juleps, Gliſters, and letting blood, which was no ſooner done, but that appeared, which they did not ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, and the Patient ſhortly dyed. Several years after, the ſaid Knight ſent up his next Son, who was now his Eldeſt; he alſo fell ſick there, and the Doctors treated him alſo in like manner; and immediately there was the ſame appearance of Pox, as in the former, which they alſo did not ſuſpect, and he alſo ſhortly dyed.</p>
            <p>As to the Jaundice, by this poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his, grounded upon <hi>Galens</hi> definition, <hi>Icterus eſt effuſio bilis in Cutem;</hi> he has confuted himſelf, for he affirms, that the <hi>Lord Er.</hi> had not the Jaundice, nor the Merchants Wife (whoſe caſe next followeth)
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:59064:68"/>notwithſtanding the cholor did dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe into the skin abundantly, where it did appear, witneſs to all that ſee them; this is not the firſt time that the Diſſector has contradicted <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> and himſelf both; but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the <hi>Alderman,</hi> faintneſs at Stomach, Laſſitude over the whole body and ſtools (in thoſe that uſe not a Milk-diet) white, not tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctured with Gall, are ſymptoms, ſufficiently warranting us to ſuſpect a Jaundice, though it did not appear in the skin; yea, the danger and greateſt pain and torment in this diſeaſe, befals the Patient general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, before the effuſion of choler into the skin. <hi>Mrs. R.</hi> of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> (whom I mention in my obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) was rackt and torn, nigh to death, for many days, whilſt there was no appearance, either in the Urine or Skin; in the ſame manner was the Merchants Wife handled,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:59064:68"/>but as ſoon as the Choler got liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to expiate into the habit of the body, both of them had eaſe. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Comforters are all Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans therefore, that cannot judge of this diſeaſe, before it appear in the skin; as to the Alderman, thoſe three Symptoms, Faintneſs at ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, Laſſitude white ſtools ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in him. Now hear his own words to <hi>Doctor Witty,</hi> the Copy of which Letter, I have by me; <hi>I conſulted</hi> Doctor Tonſtal, <hi>and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Phyſitian, as formerly, and they agreed it was the Symptom of the Jaundice; thereupon I took a Jaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice drink, by the direction of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſon, and the Eſſence of ſteel by order of</hi> Doctor Tonſtal, <hi>which I ſuppoſe is his Chalybeate, and Icte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical drinks he mentions, which by Gods Bleſſing, brought me to my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer health and condition.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:59064:69"/>
            <p>What can be ſaid more to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie any, but the Diſſector, that I was not miſtaken, in calling his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe a Jaundice, when beſides the concurrent judgment of another Phyſitian, that it was ſo,</p>
            <p>He was cured of it by a Jaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice drink, 'tis a Maxim that the beſt indication, both as to the Diag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticks, and Therapeuticks, is taken from what doth good or harm. <hi>A juvantibus &amp; nocentibus optimam ſumi indicationem,</hi> ſays <hi>Heer de Spavans,</hi> (p. 115.) Let it be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that the Diſſector, in Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Anſwer the Alderman ſent him, he has not only clipt, but counterfeited his Coin. I appeal to the Learned, in the Law of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations, what he deſerves for ſo doing; now take notice, what Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit the Diſſector is of, by theſe words, <hi>I wonder our Author did not conſult better for his own reputation,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:59064:69"/>in deſcribing this Diſeaſe, like an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, eſpecially in engaging in ſuch a deſign as this, wherein he could not think to eſcape ſo unſifted, either by my ſelf, or ſome other,</hi> (p. 84.) <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, the Jaundice he fancied, and that is all the ſign we have of it; but ſince it appeared not, it gave him a ground of ſuſpicion: I will leave it to any man of reaſon to judge, and eſpecially to thoſe of our faculty, (p.</hi> 85.) <hi>Again, 'tis well he cured, though he did not know what (p.</hi> 87.) In the caſe of the Merchants Wife, he promiſeth to evince, that I la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured <hi>under</hi> a <hi>grievous miſtake,</hi> in <hi>reference both to my Diagnosticks, about the Diſeaſe, and alſo the Cure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To anſwer this unparallel'd boaſt, firſt, I muſt ſeriouſly acknowledge the eminent hand of God, going along with me in this undertaking, when both the Mother, and Infant in her womb, were delivered from
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:59064:70"/>the ſtroke of death, ready to fall upon them ſeveral times; and let the Chriſtian Reader conſider, if the Diſſector has done like a Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Profeſſion, or rather like a ſcoffing Iſhmaelite, to ſit in his Chair at <hi>York,</hi> and blaſpheme this mercy, laughing at my Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines he underſtands not, vilifying the ſucceſs of them, he believes not, deſcribing the diſeaſe he ſaw not, and Nick-naming me a Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banck (but for that) I care not. I ſhall here preſent a Teſtimonial, ſigned with the hands of Husband and wife, and another Phyſitian, who was alſo concerned in her.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>As we do acknowledge the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, derived to us, and our Family, upon ſeveral occaſions, by the advice of <hi>Doctor Tonſtall,</hi> which he was pleaſed to crown with ſucceſs, ſo particularly, and moſt ſignally, in that caſe of the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:59064:70"/>Jaundice, which befel my Wife, after her coming from <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> big with Child; ſhe firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of a wearineſs in her Legs, going up ſtairs; ſoon after, of a moſt grievous pain in her right ſide, Ointments, and Fomentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were applyed, but did not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay it; yet as ſoon as ſhe was blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhe was at eaſe, and continued ſo three or four days; but then the ſame pain returned upon her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, which the ſecond blooding did remove, as at firſt, for other three or four days; as ſoon as the trouble began the third time to threaten her, the <hi>Doctor</hi> adviſed her to a Vomit, being aſſured (as he ſaid) that Choler only was the cauſe of all her grief; it wrought to ſatisfaction, procuring ſome mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigation of pain, yet did it after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards increaſe upon her ſo, that the <hi>Doctor</hi> did propound, if ſhe
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:59064:71"/>would admit of a third blooding, ſeeing ſhe had experienced two times before, that it was a preſent relief to her; ſhe conſented wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, and bore it without the leaſt appearance of fainting; he then gave her his Elixir in Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Wine, which in one, or two days time uſing, ſtruck forth the Jaundice ſo viſibly, that from the crown of her head, and all her body over, ſhe appeared as Yellow, as ever eyes beheld any, and then her water (but never before) was of the ſame colour, and as thick as puddle; ſhe never had the pain of her ſide, after the Jaundice ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in her skin; neither had ſhe, from firſt to laſt, the leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Fever, nor any Cough, or Spitting of Blood, that any could misjudge it for a Pleuriſie, nor any Hickough, or Singultus, that might occaſion any to fancy it the infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:59064:71"/>of the Liver; at this time, to her drink with Elixir, he added Millepedes and Jaundice Powder, which after fourteen days, reduced her to her former Complexion. She ſuppoſing her ſelf well, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted to uſe the drink any longer; the yellowneſs appeared again, he adviſed her to the Country air, and reſuming the ſame Medicine, and chewing Rhabarb by his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſhe did perfectly recover, and continued ſo, till ſhe brought forth a Son, who alſo is in Health, and well liking, as any Child, of many, God hath bleſt her withal.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William Hutchinſon.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Richard Hutchinſon.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Luke Hodgſon.</hi> 
                              <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>.</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Mountebanks Medicine (as the Diſſector is pleaſed to call it) that did the Feat is thus: <hi>R. Spirit of Nitre dulcifi'd, with Spirit of Wine, Mercury calcin'd without a
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:59064:72"/>Corroſive, diſſolved in Spirit of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, with theſe, after ſeveral Coho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bations, make a Menſtruum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With this <hi>Menſtruum,</hi> make an <hi>Elixir Proprietatis;</hi> now let the Learned judge, if the Diſſector de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve any other name, then that which he has put upon this Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine. I know all he underſtands of it, is, that there is Spirit of Wine in it, and this (ſays he) is exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hot; now I dare tell him, that here the Spirit of Wine is mixed only, and on purpoſe to refrigerate; which office of cooling it doth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, by ſweetning the fiery Acid Spirit of Nitre, which is hereby meekned, the Acute edge dinted, and reduced to ſuch a Texture of parts, as is agreeable to our conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution; inſomuch, that of this dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifi'd Spirit, one may take a ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, in a convenient Vehicle, at once; which who ſhall attempt to do with
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:59064:72"/>Spirit of well rectifyed Nitre un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulcify'd, ſhall find the <hi>Archeus</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed, a burning and corroſion in his Stomach and Bowels.</p>
            <p>I hope this much will ſuffice to ſatisfie the Reader, that the Diſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor is not a competent judge of my Medicines; but that I may for ever throw this opprobrious term upon his face.</p>
            <p>I ſhall take leave to digreſs, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to ſhow how another Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bank Medicine did the Feat (taken in a glaſs of Sack twice a day) when neither he, nor others more Learned than himſelf, could do any thing towards the recovery of their Patient, though all of them proceeded with her, <hi>Secundùm Artem,</hi> as they pleaſe to ſpeak, even till they were ſo weary, that they gave her over for one paſt help; this was the caſe of <hi>Madam Arding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> of <hi>Ardington.</hi> I ſhall tell him
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:59064:73"/>again of a third Mountebank Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, taken alſo in a glaſs of Sack every morning, did cure an Empy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em, cauſing the Child to vomit it up, every time ſhe took the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine (though it was only cordial and ſtrengthning the Archeus) till all the purulent corrupt matter, that laid in her Cheſt, above the Diaphragm, was clear gone, and ſhe perfectly well; it was the caſe of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Winchip</hi> of <hi>Chester.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the Diſſector have ſuch Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebanks Medicines, he may do well to publiſh them.</p>
            <p>Let it be here noted, that there are many Diſeaſes, called incurable, not becauſe they are ſo, <hi>Ex natura rei,</hi> but that we Phyſitians are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of Medicines, proportionable to them; and that if nature have meet aſſiſtance, it will act wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, beyond our hopes and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations.</p>
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:59064:73"/>
            <p>The Parent of this Child, would not conſent to have the Intercoſtal Muſcles pierced, thereby to let forth the purulent matter that lay in the Cheſt, which had diſtended the ribs, on that ſide, to a great height; though I told him, it was the only way in practice to cure it; yet he deſired me to try what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Medicines would do, and the Lord made them ſucceſsful.</p>
            <p>I ſhall mention another inſtance for proof hereof. A Gentlewoman had a Tumor under the Muſcles of the Abdomen, the riſe of it, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be from hard labour in Child-bearing; it encreaſed in big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs yearly, that at laſt ſhe had no reſt from pain of it; ſhe then made a long journey to <hi>London,</hi> where ſhe conſulted two Learned <hi>Doctors,</hi> famous to the world for their Books in Print. After fourteen days pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in their rational method
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:59064:74"/>with her; finding no effect, they diſmiſſed her, ſhe making ready to return home, as ſhe came, was by one, adviſed to conſult an Ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Chymiſt, <hi>Doctor Poleman,</hi> who by his <hi>Mountebank Medicines</hi> (for ſo the Diſſector will have called, all the Medicines that are not found in <hi>Londons Diſpenſatory</hi>) cauſed the humour that ſwell'd to a lump, to paſs by Urine; She obſerving his directions, was reduced to good health, and continues well; the Tumor is decreaſed, ſo that ſhe has not trouble by it. This I mention as for the honour of that worthy perſon <hi>Dr. Poleman,</hi> ſo to let the Learned conſider, that rational me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods, and Chymical Medicines, do well together, and that the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſector is like a Dog in the Manger.</p>
            <p>But to return to the Merchants Wife, <hi>p.</hi> 89. <hi>He wonders how I could make the return of her pain, in the right
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:59064:74"/>ſide, three or four times over, a ſign of the Jaundice.</hi> I anſwer, juſt as <hi>Dr. Preſton</hi> told <hi>King James,</hi> the Hound makes a Syllogiſm, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Hair to a place, where three ways met, the Dog ſmells, ſhe is not this way, nor is ſhe that way, therefore he caſts up his noſe, and concludes from the two Premiſes, that ſhe is gone the third way with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſpute, and there he finds her ſitting. So in this caſe, there is a pain in the right ſide, that blooding removes for a time, but it returns ſtill again. Where ſhall I find the Hair ſitting, that has made ſo many doubles (as the Hunters ſpeak) going forward and backward a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain? there are but three ways for it; the firſt a Plenciſe, I beat the Buſh there, I found her not, for the Woman had no Cough. The ſecond, An inflamation of the Liver, not there neither, for ſhe had not
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:59064:75"/>a Fever, nor Singultus. Therefore the third way I took, and found her ſitting in <hi>Veſica Bilaria,</hi> the Gall being there pent up by Obſtruction, a Nitro Sulphurious humour; it acted like Gunpowder fired in a Squib, or Cracker, flying upward; a terrible do it makes, till it gets liberty to vent it ſelf into the habit of the Body, as the Squib doth in the open Air, and then is quiet. Thus willing am I, to teach the Diſſector, how to hunt out Diſeaſes; but what do I ſay? all the Hounds in <hi>Hide-Park,</hi> has not the faculty of that ſenſe, ſo quick as he, for he can ſmell, not only Vitriol in <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough Spaw,</hi> where no body elſe can find it, but as if his Noſe were as long as his Ears, he can ſmell Diſeaſes from <hi>Newcastle</hi> to <hi>York,</hi> and judge of them there, better than I can do here, that am daily converſant about them. For proof
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:59064:75"/>hereof, ſee how Magiſterially he ſits on the Seat of the Scornful; <hi>What have we to prove the Jaundice, why, nothing but his ſuſpicion and jealouſie, which I wonder he would offer now the ſecond time to publick view,</hi> (p. 60.) <hi>But I muſt confeſs, I cannot but laugh at his Medicine; the Diſeaſe was a violent Fever, with an acute pain in a part; and here is a violent Medicine, which muſt needs inflame the part more, and increaſe both the Fever and the Symptoms.</hi> And as if I had laid the petrifying property of <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough</hi> water upon Nitre, which is non-ſence to ſay, he proceeds, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, that Nitre in the Spaw is ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to have petrifyed the Gall, and congealed the Choler; and here Nitre is fancyed to be the diſſolvent. I am ſorry, I am forced to point to theſe things, but I cannot avoid it, ſince they lye in my way; but really, it is
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:59064:76"/>ſuch an Hodg-potch of Art, as I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver met with before. I am afraid, my Friend will ſuffer more from his Brethren, in the faculty, about this Diſeaſe, and its Sign, Symptoms, and Cure expreſſed, than he did by the Woman, about ſo often bleeding, and vomiting this</hi> Gentlewoman.</p>
            <p>(<hi>Pag.</hi> 90.) Now he will have it an inflamation, and therefore, <hi>I ſhould have conſulted</hi> Hippocrates, <hi>for cooling, and opening Medicines; but it may be he will ſay, he does not approve of the old method that uſes hot things in Fevers; it appears ſo indeed, in the mean time, that Patient is to be pityed, that muſt be ſo treated. I have had occaſion to ſpeak to this Point, in my anſwer to</hi> Dr. Simpſon, <hi>and therefore I'le ſay no more now, ſince there is little danger of any young Students to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Proſelytes to the Author that ſhall obſerve, either his deſcription
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:59064:76"/>of Diſeaſes, or the ſucceſs of his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines.</hi> But as if he would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant his laſt Clauſe. (the ſucceſs of my Medicines) Dr. <hi>Tonſtall is to blame, for chalenging to himſelf the Honour of this Cure, which was due to God alone; who beyond all hopes in defect of due means, does often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times grant a ſignal recovery,</hi> (p. 92.) It ſeems when the Diſſector ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies due means for cure, and the party recovers, the Honour is not then due to God alone, but he muſt go half with him in it; as for me, I diſclaim all right and title there, and gives it to him, that works in us, both to will and to do of his own good pleaſure. But yet, as if the Gentlewoman or the Child was dead, ſuppoſing I miſtake the Diſeaſe, he is poſitive in this; <hi>If the Phyſitian miſtake the Diſeaſe, he muſt undoubtedly fail of the Cure:</hi> Though I grant this to be true, he
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:59064:77"/>contradicts himſelf, for in the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermans caſe, before he declares, <hi>I cured, though I did not know what.</hi> Again, (p. 95.) <hi>As he miſtook in his Diagnosticks, or judging of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, ſo I muſt in kindneſs to him, and his buſineſs for the future (if he will not accept it ſo) let him know that he was out of his Theraputicks, that Ternary Spirit of Wine, Nitre,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>being as improper, as any thing he could have pitcht upon.</hi> Thus, ſays he, <hi>I have ſifted theſe three caſes of the Jaundice,</hi> that is, by Lies and Tales, he has ſhifted them off as well as he could. But where will the Diſſector find refuge, to excuſe all this mallepert bitterneſs vented againſt me, only for doing my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſo well to this Gentlewoman, that ſhe, and all her Relations, bleſſes God that did direct me in the performance of it; why, 'tis here <hi>I was told ſo,</hi> the very ſame
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:59064:77"/>anſwer, which in my hearing he gave to the Apothecary of <hi>York,</hi> charging him that he had Printed a Lye, to the reproach of <hi>Doctor Simpſon</hi> in his practice; and that the Widow, whoſe Husband dyed, would take her Oath before any Magiſtrate, to witneſs as much.</p>
            <p>He now (<hi>p.</hi> 96.) to ballance his charge againſt <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> that it occaſions the Jaundice, as I have inſtanced in theſe three caſes; he tells of two, that the Water cured of the ſame Diſeaſe: I ſhall here record another inſtance to like pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and then it will appear, that there is two to one on my ſide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Diſſector. <hi>Sir Watkinſon Paler,</hi> troubled with <hi>Hypochondiack</hi> wind, conſulted <hi>Doctor Witty,</hi> who adviſed him to drink <hi>Scarbrough</hi> for his Cure; he obſerved all his directions, as to Preparatives, order of drinking and Phyſick;
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:59064:78"/>ſuch as he pleaſed to preſcribe; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all his ſtrict obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of theſe rules, inſtead of a Cure by the Water, he contracted the Jaundice, and in ſuch an height and manner, that it ſtaid with him all the Winter following, though he uſed means, all he could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure to reſiſt it. Thus much I had from his own mouth, who came on purpoſe to <hi>Knaisbrough,</hi> to adviſe with me two years ago; ever ſince he makes uſe of the <hi>Sulpher</hi> Well there, to his advantage; and though the Diſſector was ſo impudent, as to perſwade him againſt his own experience, to return to <hi>Scarbrough</hi> laſt year, yet he is ſo wiſe, as to uſe it no longer, but continues in his reſolution for <hi>Knaisbrough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now (<hi>p.</hi> 97.) he takes in hand to Plow with my Heffer, telling a ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of my Wife, wherein there is not one tittle of truth, more than
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:59064:78"/>that, ſhe came to me at <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> as I had appointed her, before I came from <hi>Newcaſtle;</hi> and when ſhe was come, one morning being on the Hill with the Ladies, I called her down, and when ſhe came, I told the Diſſector that ſhe was my Wife, I bid her diſcourſe with my Brother, ſo they walked together; to this day, I never asked her what he ſaid or adviſed; having done it ſolely in point of Honour to him, as a piece of Civility, which one Brother owes to another, as to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint him with my Wife; She neither took Preparatives before, nor Phyſick with, nor after her Water, but ſtaid above a week, and returned with her Father, who came there for the Gravel and Stone, but will do ſo no more. As to the Marginal Note, <hi>That he is unthankful.</hi> I declare the contrary, for I thank God, ſhe got not the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:59064:79"/>harm by <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> which I did, yet he hath the face to make the world believe, that I ſent for her thither, on purpoſe to take his advice.</p>
            <p>I grant what he ſays, (<hi>pag.</hi> 98.) <hi>That it is common for</hi> Scarbrough, <hi>to take down thoſe that are Corpulent,</hi> by reaſon of the ſharpneſs of the Salts in it; it is either good for that, or for nothing; but I deny his Inference, which ſays, <hi>it could not poſſibly be done, if it were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive;</hi> if it were only obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, his Inference were good; but who ſays ſo, <hi>Scarbrough</hi> it is purging alſo.</p>
            <p>He proceeds, (<hi>p.</hi> 99.) <hi>Nor is there a better thing in Nature, for taking away the reliques of all inveterate Agues.</hi> How can I believe this brag, when <hi>Mr. Tailor</hi> of <hi>York,</hi> his own <hi>Apothecary,</hi> was ordered by the Diſſector, after his Ague Fits had
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:59064:79"/>left him, to come to <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> and drink water, who did ſo, and after the firſt days drinking, inſtead of taking away the reliques of the Ague, it brought his Fits upon him again, and he was glad to return, whether more Wiſe man, he, or the Diſſector that adviſed him thither, I leave the Reader to judge: This was told me, whilſt I was at <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough,</hi> by <hi>Mr. Taylor</hi> himſelf.</p>
            <p>He goes on, (<hi>p.</hi> 100.) <hi>But I may not paſs it over, that our Author was cenſured, and fell under the obloquy of the Women, concerning the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants Wife;</hi> yet I thank him, he ſays, <hi>I do indeed, take him to be an honeſt Man, and faithful Phyſitian.</hi> It ſeems, if I had not been ſo then, I had eſcaped both his and their obloquy; yet what I ſaid in my juſt defence, he ſays, <hi>It ſavours too much like that of a Phariſee.</hi> p. 102.</p>
            <p>I ſhall here ſhew you the Diſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:59064:80"/>fair out-ſide profeſſion, that by the ſequel it may appear, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he or I be more like an Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, the true note of a Phariſee, ſays he, (<hi>p.</hi> 125.) <hi>As I deſire in all all things to be found faithful, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes me, either as a Phyſitian or a Chriſtian, ſo in this diſpute, I aim not ſo much at</hi> Victory <hi>as</hi> Truth. Here then is truth unqueſtionable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt Truth, Scarbrough</hi> Water has Stone-powder in it, leaving it in Sand at the bottom of the Veſſel when 'tis boyled.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Second Truth, Scarbrough</hi> Spaw is parallel to the Dropping Well at <hi>Knaisbrough,</hi> which leaves alſo Sand, at the bottom of the Veſſel in boyling.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Third,</hi> The Water that leaves Sand at the bottom of the Veſſel, when boyled, has a Lapideſcent juice, and is petrifying; 'tis his own ſaying.</p>
            <pb n="129" facs="tcp:59064:80"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourth,</hi> The Water that has a Lapideſcent juice, and is petrify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is bad for the Stone, Gout, and Jaundice, by natural conſequence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifth,</hi> 'Tis the peculiar Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of <hi>Scarbrough Spaw,</hi> whereby it is diſtinguiſhed from all other Spaws that are in uſe, to take a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty Jadiſh Fit ſooner or later.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixth,</hi> Allom-ſtone diſſolved in water, gives a Purple Tincture (with Gall) this Allom-ſtone, he confeſſeth, is in <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> and therefore the Tincture by Gall, is no Argument for Vitriol in <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough Spaw.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventh,</hi> That all waters that have diſſolved Iron, hath Vitriol alſo, as the product of that diſſolution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eighth,</hi> All the Salts that ſproots out of the Cliff, is Nitroaluminous, and not Vitriol.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ninth,</hi> The three Carts load of Earth, fallen from the Cliff, is not
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:59064:81"/>Iron-ſtone, but Earth petrifyed, mixt with pebble ſtones.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tenth,</hi> The precipitated powder found in the bottom of the Veſſel, after <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Water has ſtood in it two or three days, is Glebe of <hi>Allom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eleventh,</hi> If Vitriol be joyned with Nitre in <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Water (as the Diſſector will have it) he makes it a corroſive water, which is worſe than all I have ſaid againſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Twelfth,</hi> The Diſſector muſt yeild the <hi>Victory</hi> to the Anatomizer, for <hi>Truth</hi> ſake, or elſe— in Print.</p>
            <p>As to the Tenth Propoſition (all the reſt being proved already) if it be demanded how I can make it out, I anſwer firſt, to the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Diſſector in his Letter to <hi>R. S.</hi> ſays, that when the Spaw Water is firſt ſet on the fire, this Powder ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles to the bottom; I grant it, but after the water by boyling, hath
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:59064:81"/>let fall the ſtone-power in it, then doth the Saline water reſume this powder into its Pores, and after all the Salts are ſetled into Chryſtals, you ſhall find it in the remaining water, and may ſee that it differs nothing from the Glebe of Allom, if one may truſt his ſenſes, as I have mentioned, which I have to ſhow, as to the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, take this account, The Nitrous water meeting with the Allom ſtone, corrodes and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves it wholly. During this acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the water appears clear, but as ſoon as the Inteſtine motion ceaſeth, that the Nitre and Allom embrace mutually each other in quiet, then is the Glebe of Allom as an Hete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogenious, <hi>Caput mortuum,</hi> caſt forth of the embracements of theſe two Salts, and ſo ſettles to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, which happens in two or three days time.</p>
            <p>If it be demanded further, how it
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:59064:82"/>comes to paſs, that the Glebe of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom ſhould ſettle to the bottom, and yet the ſtone-powder which is alſo in it, and a heavier body, doth not ſettle at all, whilſt the water is kept in cold, from boiling on the fire. I anſwer, here is the difference betwixt petrifying wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and Mineral waters; theſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, ſooner or later, do ſettle ſomething to the bottom, the other do not, as is known by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; the reaſon of the difference may be gathered from that I ſaid laſt; for the Stone, whilſt the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line water diſſolves it, is meerly paſſive in that action of diſſolution; and therefore the longer a Nitrous water has ſtone in its Bowels, the firmlier it holds it, there being nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sulphur, nor other Salt in it, to re-act upon the Nitre. It is not ſo when Metallick, or Mineral Stones are diſſolved in water; there are
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:59064:82"/>then contrary principles at work; the ſtrife being ended, they ſhew what Metal or Mineral thoſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters come from by their ſettlements.</p>
            <p>He now remembers what he had forgotten, (<hi>p.</hi> 103.) <hi>But there is one thing I may not over-look;</hi> the ſtones, that were by <hi>Phyſick,</hi> brought out of the Gall, which the Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor at <hi>London</hi> did ſhew us. <hi>He is afraid I was miſtaken,</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 104.) So is the ſaying ſtill of the things I ſee with mine eyes; but why? <hi>What paſſage is there from the Gall to the Guts to convey ſtones?</hi> the ſtones he ſhewed us, were larger in bredth, than Gray-Peaſe, being flatter, but about their bigneſs; if he denies theſe paſſable through the <hi>Ductus Bilarius,</hi> he has little or no experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the works of Nature, as I have inſtanced before, when 'tis aſſiſted by Art; next he accuſeth me for aſſerting upon the former
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:59064:83"/>Principles of the petrifying Nature of <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> that is ill for the Gout, which I experienced in my ſelf, and he oppoſeth it only by his experience of himſelf, who has had ſome gentle Fits of it, and ſo leaves it, <hi>making himſelf both Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff and Witneſs, and Judge of this matter;</hi> but this is ſpoken to here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p>Next he declares (<hi>p.</hi> 105.) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, for commending <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough,</hi> that it is ſo quick in its purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing quality, that it needs no Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative, and rather than loſe his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of doſing out his Phyſick, he doth diſcommend the water, as much as I can think it deſerves; 'tis an old ſaying, better may one ſteal a Gooſe, than another ſtick down a Feather; his words are theſe, <hi>The water is,</hi> (p. 106.) <hi>indeed nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ſometimes has wrought ten days together, while yet it has but
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:59064:83"/>made a furrow through the Guts, and has left all the Excrementicious hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours behind it, the party finding therein no benefit at all.</hi> 'Tis ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly ſaid of the Diſſector, now this ſecond time; I ſee truth will come out at laſt, <hi>Therefore he ſays, there is a neceſſity both to prepare by purging before, and alſo in the drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Water; otherwiſe, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the daily working of the water, they may return as they came;</hi> 'tis well, if it ſo fall out, that they return not worſe. Having thus diſcommended the ineffectual pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of the Waters purging, in that it makes but a furrow through the Bowels, and leaves all the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crementicious humours behind, he faceth about (<hi>p.</hi> 107.) and does commend it as ſingular incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of other Spaw waters, that are not purging. Firſt, in regard <hi>of the Stone, in this caſe waters that
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:59064:84"/>are only Diuretical, may cauſe an Iſchuria, by carrying ſlimy humours into the ſmallar Veſſels;</hi> 'Tis grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if no Phyſitians be there, that has ſo much wit, as to prevent this danger, by giving the Patient a Purge. Secondly, (<hi>p.</hi> 108.) <hi>By the purging property of the Water, not only the groſs Excrementicious hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, but alſo the ſtone filings that are in the water, muſt be carried the broad way down the Bowels.</hi> Alas for him, ſurely, the man is unadviſed, thus in one Page, to write <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con;</hi> if the water purging ten days together, could not carry away <hi>the light Cherry-ſtones that were in the Bowels,</hi> as he inſtances, (<hi>p.</hi> 106.) How can it be ſuppoſed, that it ſhould Purge away the Stone-file<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, which beſide their gravity, has affixedneſs upon the inner coats of the Bowels? like as we ſee the Sand cleaving to the ſides of the
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:59064:84"/>Chamber-pot, which will not be waſhed off with water, unleſs rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be uſed. Thirdly, <hi>This purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing property of the water, does quite overthrow what before I ſaid, aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the waters obſtructive property, for 'tis impoſſible that the ſame thing ſhould be purgative, and alſo obstru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive.</hi> In this conteſt with <hi>Hydrol. Chym.</hi> he uſed the term Sir <hi>Simpſon,</hi> as a reproach; for my part, I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how the Diſſector got his Batchelor of Arts degree, if he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted after this manner; had he ſaid the water <hi>quatenus</hi> purging, could not be obſtructive, it had been ſomething; purging and bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, are terms more oppoſite, than purging and obſtructing; yet Rha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard the ſame thing doth perform both, becauſe of its different parts. <hi>Scarbrough</hi> purgeth, as it is enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Allom and Nitre; it ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs alſo, by the plenty of Sand
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:59064:85"/>Sand and Clay that is in it; may not different things in the ſame wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, have different effects? Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (<hi>p.</hi> 109.) <hi>That property which I charge on it, as that it cauſeth the Gout, cannot poſſibly conſiſt with the purging quality of the water, for purging is owned by all, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed as a ſpecial remedy againſt the Gout, either to prevent or to cure it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſaid the riſe of this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, was from a petrifying proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of an Acid Spirit; I know none but the Diſſector (who refers the cauſe of all things to the firſt qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of heat and cold) that doth oppoſe me in this; the inſtance which Mr. <hi>Clarke,</hi> one of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Juſtices for the Peace, in <hi>Northumberland,</hi> told me, which he ſee with his eyes, is famous to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it; Mr. <hi>Potter,</hi> Steward to the Earl of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> extremely troubled with the Gout, had fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:59064:85"/>Sand and ſmall Stones, that came forth through the Pores, and ſtood on all the joynts of his fingers on the out-ſide of the skin; this being ſo, <hi>Sylvins</hi> and with him, all experienced Authors, give as a Maxim, that Acidities are ſo far from being corrected, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved by purging (with any Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick that is vulgarly known) that it doth but exaſperate them, and make them worſe.</p>
            <p>Yet I'le grant his Propoſition; what will it avail? to bring it down particularly to the purging with <hi>Scarbrough</hi> in this Diſeaſe; nothing at all; for by his own confeſſion, it makes but a furrow through the Bowels, and leaves all the Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menticious humours behind. But he will ſay, I'le mend that matter by giving other Phyſick, mean while,
'tis the purging with his Phyſick, and not the waters purging, that
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:59064:86"/>cures the Gout. But then I ask, will his purge mend the petrifying property that is in the water, and that Acidity, becauſe of the Dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicate Salt in it, both which are Enemies to the Gout? I trow not; as <hi>Scarbrough</hi> therefore doth upon theſe two accounts, exalt and aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the ſpecifick cauſe of this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, as it cannot cure it, much leſs can it prevent it. <hi>John</hi> Lord <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſſes,</hi> complained this year, that by drinking <hi>Scarbrough</hi> but 3 or 4 days, it gave him a Fit of the Gout; if the Diſſector will perſiſt, that he can cure the Gout, and prevent it by purging, then, I ſuppoſe, he is maſter of <hi>Helmonts Arcanum coral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linum.</hi> I adviſe him to preſent it to the <hi>R. S.</hi> which may make amends for the laſt trouble he gave them; he concludes, <hi>And therefore ſeeing he had projected to fix ſo ſevere a charge upon the Spaw, I wonder he
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:59064:86"/>did not take care ſo to draw it up, as that one piece might not interfer with, and conſute another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I judge, that the Reader has more cauſe to wonder at him, why he ſhould ſay ſo.</p>
            <p>He now ſummons up all his forces together, and ſays, that Chymical Writers lead the Van; <hi>Acidity, Inky ſmell, and black Tincture from Gall, are certain and undeniable Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to prove Vitriol.</hi> Thus he builds Caſtles in the Air, I ſhall blow them all down with this one breath; <hi>where?</hi> not in <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> nor any other water that has Nitre and Allom; there theſe three Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties prove nothing for Vitriol, for Nitre will give the Acidity, Allom the Tincture without it; as for the Inky ſmell, as he alone doth find it, I gave him an Experiment to make it more perceptable to the ſenſe of ſmelling, from whence it
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:59064:87"/>proceeds, namely, Allom. The ſavour of any thing, is from the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurious parts, whilſt they are freed from their Vincula Salina, and ſends forth the Effluvium, which effects the Organ of ſmelling; thus Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, till the Body be opened, ſmells little or nothing, but diſſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and precipitated, how ſtrong is the ſence of it? from the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, the Allom in the Spaw is not diſtinguiſhable by ſmell, but let all the Saline parts ſettle into Chryſtals, after the ſtone-powder is ſeparated, and take the Sulphu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious part that remains, dry it, and diſſolve it in hot water, as I ſaid (<hi>p.</hi> 59.) of my Book, and then you will find it gives the ſame ſmell that the Allom Pans at <hi>Whitby</hi> do, and ſtronger.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee his threefold Cord is eaſily broken at one ſnap; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve now his Pedantick, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcholar-like
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:59064:87"/>dealing with me: <hi>I wonder to find him ſo zealous in this Point, to fix a ſtincking ſmell upon that water, when there are ſo many thouſands to confute him; though hence it may appear he has lost his ſmell, yet I ſhould be ſorry, that for ſo ſmall a miſtake, my Friend ſhould forfeit his Noſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have loſt my underſtanding, if the Diſſector forfeit my Creſt and Coat of Arms, whilſt he writes of <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Spaw againſt me.</p>
            <p>He ſays (<hi>p.</hi> 111.) the inſtance I gave of <hi>Hunwick Well,</hi> makes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to my purpoſe; for this, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Reader to my Book (<hi>p.</hi> 53. and 54.) But <hi>why may not that water have the Vitriol of Iron in it;</hi> 'tis granted that it has, for how can it partake of Iron, and be without the Vitriol; and how can it give the Tincture by Gall, but from Iron. What then, is this his <hi>may-be</hi> to his
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:59064:88"/>purpoſe, that goes about to prove that the Tincture from Gall, is not from Iron, but from the Vitriol? to this I ſhall ſpeak anon, all the matter the Diſſector has to brag on againſt me, is occaſioned by my civility to him, for this ſee (<hi>p.</hi> 97.) Concerning my Wife; ſo here, becauſe at my firſt coming, I gave him leave to ſay what he pleaſed, and did not contradict him in a word, therefore 'tis put in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, <hi>I have changed my mind.</hi> He is now for a work of Supereroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (<hi>p.</hi> 112.) <hi>Becauſe I would do ſomething more</hi> (which is as much as nothing at all) <hi>For this my friends Conviction, I ſhall</hi> ex abundanti, <hi>caſt him in one Author more, and he is a Chymiſt too,</hi> Faber. Hidrell. Chym. (<hi>pag.</hi> 38.) <hi>where treating of Springs that has imbibed Sulphur and Vitriol; the water,</hi> ſays he, <hi>of theſe Fountains, turn black with Gall, and
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:59064:88"/>that is as true and undoubted Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony that there is Vitriol in it.</hi> The Diſſector will ſtill be dabling with Chymical Authors, and does but bemire himſelf with them; for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, he cites <hi>Swelfer</hi> againſt <hi>Dr. S.</hi> that Vitriol of Iron will Calcine white in a Cruſible, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the knowledge of every <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> Chyrurgion; he cited <hi>Faber</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (<hi>p.</hi> 66.) directly againſt himſelf.</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>ex abundanti,</hi> to ſignifie that he underſtands not the ſcope of their Writings, he cites him here again, whilſt he is treating only of theſe Spaws, that has imbibed <hi>Sulphur</hi> and <hi>Vitriol;</hi> and will tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer his inference he makes of the Gall tincturing thoſe waters, to be an Argument for <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> that has imbibed Allom. If <hi>Faber</hi> were alive, he would not bear this abuſe of <hi>Dr. Witty,</hi> who would make him ſpeak, that the <hi>Spaw</hi> that has Allom
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:59064:89"/>in it, if it tincture black by putting Gall to it, then 'tis an undoubted Argument that it has diſſolved Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol. Chymiſts, are more ſearching by their Experiments into the truth of things, then to give a general Propoſition from what is true, but in ſome, not all waters.</p>
            <p>He would fain know, <hi>p.</hi> 115. <hi>How it comes to paſs that white Vitriol will make Ink?</hi> For ſatisfaction, I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain refer him to the Author he has not ſeen, <hi>Tachen. Hippoc.</hi> (p. 130.) <hi>Vitriolum album illud de Goſlaria, &amp; ut illud de Carinithia participant quidem de Marte, &amp; venere, non tamen ſunt divites acidi naturalis ob id admodum pigrè ingreſcunt cum Gallis. Dr. W.</hi> accuſeth <hi>Dr. S.</hi> in his Epiſtle to the Reader, <hi>That he fell among many ill Books, and read unwholſom Authors.</hi> If this had not been <hi>Dr. Witty</hi>'s own Lott, he had not fallen into the Pinfold, nor
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:59064:89"/>rendred himſelf ſo trifling a writer of Mineral waters. Becauſe I ſtill perſiſt to owe him the kindneſs of a Friend, that he may underſtand Vitriol the better, I commend to his reading <hi>Caneparius de Atramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis; Dr. W.</hi> thinks I am of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, ready to quarrel with any one that differ in opinion from me; <hi>Will he fall out with the Author of Hydrel Chym.</hi> ſays he. I Anſwer no. Truly I leave that to the Diſſector.</p>
            <p>That which I ſaw with mine eyes, he is ever telling I may be miſtaken in, ſays he, (<hi>p.</hi> 115.) <hi>I am afraid the Apothecary was too nimble for the Doctor;</hi> It is true, he is too nimble in his diſcourſe againſt <hi>Dr. Witty, He took the Stone out of the Vitrio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line bed, with which the water was tinctured by Gall. Dr. Witty</hi> did then approve of it to be an Allom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, and was confident it would not give Tincture by Gall, till he
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:59064:90"/>ſee the contrary, <hi>S. W. Davis,</hi> and his Brother being preſent. Now he has bethought himſelf of this eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, 'twas taken out of the Vitriol Bed, (<hi>p.</hi> 116.)</p>
            <p>'Tis a ſhame that the Diſſector ſhould be ſuffered to ſhift off plain Truths, with falſe Surmiſes, giving the Reader to believe, that there is a Vitrioline Bed near the Water; if it were ſo, why did he not, firſt, extract the Vitriol, and have it to ſhew? 'tis eaſily done; by all the ſearch we can make in all the Beds thereabouts, we Extract nothing but plain Allom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He contents himſelf with proving</hi> Knaisbrough Spaw <hi>to be Vitrioline, by the Yellow colour it precipitates.</hi> I am proving no ſuch matter, for I know that Cole-water, yea, a Spring that runs through the rotten roots of Trees, will do the like; 'tis true that, I ſay, Vitrioline water
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:59064:90"/>precipitates by Sanding, a Yellow colour; but it doth not therefore follow that the yellow precipitation is a proof for Vitriol, as he would have me to infer. <hi>Dr. S.</hi> alſo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes me, in what I mean by eaſily precipitating; I underſtand by it, in ſo ſhort a time, as two or three days, I there ſay, (<hi>p.</hi> 56. and 57.) that <hi>Scarbrough</hi> ſetling of it ſelf in ſo ſhort a time, a black Sediment cannot be <hi>Terra Vitrioli;</hi> firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I judge that it was never ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that any Vitrioline water, did by ſtanding, caſt down its other ſo quickly.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That this differs in colour from the other; whoever pleaſe to try it, ſhall ſee, that as ſoon as <hi>Scarbrough</hi> caſts down this Sediment, 'tis black.</p>
            <p>The Diſſector has now got to the Pinfold, (<hi>p.</hi> 117.) as his deſerved Haven; 'tis his ſingular Art to be
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:59064:91"/>ſtrict in tything <hi>Annis, Mint,</hi> and <hi>Cummin;</hi> but the great things, the pillars on which the diſpute lies, he neglects, and lightly paſſeth them over with a, <hi>The truth is, 'tis nothing more than a frivolous conceit, and not worthy to be replyed to;</hi> So he ſpeaks, (<hi>p.</hi> 73.) He tells us, <hi>That the Pinder of Wakefield could not hold him,</hi> he was <hi>very well delivered with his bones whole.</hi> I have cauſe to ſay ſomething, ſure I am, the Air that got into his <hi>Peritonaeum,</hi> of the imaginary victory over <hi>Dr. S.</hi> hath made him ſwell with rage, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, and revenge againſt me. Let the Reader now view the Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</p>
            <p>Thus the Diſſector argues, the Tincture by Gall is not from Allom, nor from Iron; <hi>Ergo,</hi> it is from Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol.</p>
            <p>I Reply, if not from Iron, then not from Vitriol; <hi>Ergo,</hi> It is from Allom.</p>
            <pb n="151" facs="tcp:59064:91"/>
            <p>If the Cuckow of <hi>York,</hi> be for ever able, in the judgment of all the Chymiſts in <hi>Europe,</hi> either to creep out, or over-top this Pinfold, I ſhall ſubmit to be called the <hi>Pindar</hi> of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> whilſt I live. As for <hi>Gotham Colledge,</hi> I did imagine 'twas only to be found in <hi>Eutopia;</hi> but now I do retract, taking it for granted, the Diſſector has had his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation there. <hi>Vitriol</hi> of what ſort ſoever, is a Metal diſſolved; this is an undoubted truth, made good by Experiment upon all Vitriols; both Natural, ſuch as are got out of the Bowels of the Earth, and Artificial, ſuch as are made by diſſolving any Metals, and exhaling of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvents. Each one of theſe Vitri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ols will diſſolve in water, and by an Alkali put to it, will precipitate the Body of the Metal contained in it. Let us now deſcend from this General Propoſition, to the
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:59064:92"/>particular Vitriol of Iron, which the Diſſector affirms is in <hi>Scarbrough</hi> water, and I will ſuppoſe it to be there; the queſtion now is, what is it, that the Gall put into the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, doth precipitate? is it not the body of the Iron which was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in it, according to the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral rule of all Vitriols, which by precipitation is made to appear, and ſettles as an heavy Body to the bottom? Thus is the Tincture by Gall, from Iron, made plain and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; and therefore as he excludes Iron from giving Tincture by Gall in <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> he muſt exclude Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol alſo; for this Vitriol is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more, than Iron diſſolved with Spirit of Sulphur; and ſo it follows, that it muſt be from Allom by his own confeſſion. Thus has he brought himſelf into the Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, there let him be. But the Reader may ask how is it, that the
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:59064:92"/>Allom in the water, gives the Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture by Gall? I anſwer, in a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel manner to Vitriol, as was ſaid at firſt; as it is proved in Vitri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oline Waters, that it is from the body of the Metal, not from the Spirit, Sulphur, that diſſolved it, that the Gall precipitates; ſo here 'tis not from the juice of the Allom, but from the body of the Glebe, a Terreſtrial and Sulphurous matter, which gives the Tincture. I prove it by this Experiment, take the Allom water out of any Trough at <hi>Whithy,</hi> which is the infuſion of Burnt Allom-ſtone, and put Gall to it, and it will Tincture; but take the very ſame water without the Addition of any thing, and Boil it until it caſt to the bottom the Earthy Sulphurous parts, which the Workmen call Slam, and then that Water will not tinck with Gall.</p>
            <pb n="154" facs="tcp:59064:93"/>
            <p>He repeats (<hi>p.</hi> 118.) what he ſaid before, that the Earth <hi>falling from the Cliff, near the Spaw, is converted into Iron ſtone.</hi> I ſuppoſe, by this, he would have us to believe, <hi>Ovid Metamorphoſis</hi> is no Poetical Ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but real Truth, that this Earth was converted into Iron ſtone, as <hi>Lot's</hi> Wife was into a Pillar of Salt, by a Miracle, on purpoſe, that the Spaw might be made to ſtrengthen the Natural parts, by the property of Iron. The anſwer I gave to it, he can no more make ſenſe of it, than of the plain poſition of <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> which I expounded to him, and ſhall do this, I ſaid at firſt it did appear to me (now that I have tryed it) I affirm it to be nothing elſe, than what I ſaid before, Earth (wherein are abundance of pebble ſtones of ſeveral ſorts) impregnated with ſtore of Nitro Aluminous Salt, as all the Cliff is, ſliding
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:59064:93"/>down by ſome daſh of rain upon the Sands; as ſoon as the ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous moiſture is exhaled from it by Sun and Air, it then Petrifies, and is as a Rock lying there. I declare there is as much Gold as Iron in it, I wonder he did not ſay ſo, for the ſame Argument which he uſeth for Iron, namely, that it fluxeth in the fire, would have ſerved to make it Gold; this had been as good an Artifice for bringing Moulter to his Mill, as all the Hyperboles of <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough</hi> water; his Patients then might ſatisfie both their thirſt and hunger, <hi>Auri ſacra fames.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſaid that Allom ſtone diſſolved in water, would Tincture with Gall; I mentioned Spirit of Nitre, mixed with Water, for a diſſolvent, as freeſt from exception; he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, <hi>Alas</hi> Dr. S. <hi>ſaid ſo, nor does he weild the Club much better, or has any new guard,</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 119.)</p>
            <pb n="156" facs="tcp:59064:94"/>
            <p>The man is in a dream certainly, the <hi>Logomachia,</hi> betwixt him and <hi>Dr. S.</hi> was, indeed, playing with Foyls or Cudgels; what tells he me of a Club? his diſſecting, and my Anatomizing is, fighting with ſharps; is it ſo long ſince I met with him on the Hills (near <hi>Knais<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough</hi> Town) they are to him the Mountains of <hi>Gilboa,</hi> where he did manfully fall upon his own Sword point, (<hi>p.</hi> 56.) Where was <hi>his New Guard</hi> then, not in his Breeches, for his Bum has been well paid, more than once or twice, (<hi>p.</hi> 20.31.51.)</p>
            <p>He cites my Argument, (<hi>p.</hi> 120.) againſt <hi>Vitriol</hi> in <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> but ſays nothing to diſprove it, only he calls it my <hi>Battering-kam,</hi> and leaves it to my Wife to confute; I am perſwaded ſhe is as able as the Diſſector to do ſo. He compares me to <hi>Joab,</hi> he conſiders not, that
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:59064:94"/>the compariſon lies fully upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; for who ſo great a Friend to <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> as the Diſſector? and he out of his ſimple Friendſhip to it, will plead to have Vitriol there, where alſo is Nitre; and in this he does not leſs againſt <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> than <hi>Joab</hi> did to <hi>Abner,</hi> in ſmiting him into the fifth rib, making the water thereby corroſive. I retort his own words, <hi>Is this a token of his Friendſhip, to make it poyſonous?</hi> But ſays he (<hi>p.</hi> 121.) <hi>What have we to do with the Spirits of Vitriol and Nitre?</hi> why? if their bodies be in the water, they cannot be without their Spirits. Such as the Spirits are, ſuch are the Bodies from whence they are drawn; corroſive both, only the Bodies are not ſo active as the Spirits. <hi>But,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Rye-bread distilled, will afford an extreme corroſive Spirit, that will diſſolve Metal, if he will truſt</hi>
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:59064:95"/>Mr. <hi>Boyle.</hi> This is the ſecond time, he has abuſed this worthy Author, making him ſpeak point blank con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his very deſign, the ſecond part of his Experiment Philoſ. <hi>p.</hi> 88. his words are theſe; <hi>Since I have obſerved it to be the main thing that keeps Judicious Men from ſeeking, or ſo much as hoping for Noble Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvents, that they are ſcarce to be perſwaded there can be conſiderably piercing Menſtrums, that are not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably corroſive. I will here acquaint you with a Liquor, that may, I preſume, aſſiſt you, to undeceive ſome of them.</hi> Thus you ſee the Author brings in this diſtilled wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, of Rye-bread, as an Argument to perſwade others, that there may be Liquors Diſſolvent, which are not corroſive; the Diſſector ſays this ſame <hi>is extremely corroſive,</hi> citing Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi> for it: Spirit of Volatile Salt of Tartar, is a great
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:59064:95"/>Diſſolvent, it is not therefore cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſive; ſo much may be ſaid of <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culatum minus &amp; majus Paracelſi Ens veneris pole manui,</hi> which <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont</hi> declares to be as ſweet as Honey (to ſay nothing of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor Alkeheſt.) Sallet-Oyl will diſſolve Brimſtone (which Aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortis cannot do) is it therefore cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſive? let it be noted alſo, that the Diſſector ſays, we muſt believe Mr. <hi>Boyle,</hi> that the water of Rye bread diſtilled, will diſſolve Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal; another untruth charged upon him, which is contrary to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Maxim of Chymiſtry, <hi>Similia ſimilibus Diſſolvuntur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He goes to my laſt Charge, and ſays, (<hi>p.</hi> 123.) <hi>I have often known Inveterated Diſſenteries, and other Fluxes, cured by it;</hi> he has told the <hi>R. S.</hi> that <hi>Hecticks</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions</hi> are cured by it; and now Diſſenteries, when the Third Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:59064:96"/>comes forth, he will tell us of broken Bones, and Limbs out of joint, are cured by it; there's as much reaſon for this, as the other. A Merchant in this Town, was brought into a deſperate Flux, and hardly ſcaped with life, by drinking of it but two or three days.</p>
            <p>Another inſtance of one at <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough,</hi> a luſty young man, Son to one of the Officers of the Cuſtom, whilſt I was there, by drinking but two or three days, had ſuch a Flux, that he was pined near to a Conſumption, before it could be remedied.</p>
            <p>I urged the Diſſector with his promiſe to <hi>Dr. S.</hi> that he would deal accordingly with me, in the laſt words of my Book; to which he gives this anſwer, (<hi>p.</hi> 124.) <hi>But as for this Piece, I ſee not the leaſt point of Art in it, from the beginning to the end; I refer it to the Learned
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:59064:96"/>and Impartial Reader, to judge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us;</hi> In this we are agreed.</p>
            <p>Having done with the Diſſector, I ſhall relate only the ſtory of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumbus.</hi> After he had firſt diſcovered the way to the <hi>Indies,</hi> taking the <hi>Spaniards</hi> along with him, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected performance of promiſe from them; they requited him with this Anſwer, 'Twas no Art at all to Sail thither; he then took up an Egg, and bid them make it ſtand upright upon the Table, they made an eſſay, but could not; he then did it before them. Here is no Art, 'tis true (ſaid he) in making the Egg to ſtand upright, yet could not you do it, till I ſhewed you how.</p>
            <p>Let <hi>Dr. Witty</hi> apply this ſtory to himſelf, and what follows, (<hi>p.</hi> 123.) <hi>I am of opinion, that an angry fit is very wholſome for ſome conſtitutions, though it may make a man uneaſie
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:59064:97"/>in his company for the preſent, and thoſe that are within his reach, yet when the Ebullition of Choler is over, it leaves a man in a far more ſedate temper of mind, for a good while after, than before he was wont to be, and more Gay and Complacent in his humour to others: If my Friend having given his Spleen this vent, be the better for it in his Cranium, I ſhould be very glad.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:59064:97"/>
            <head>To the Brethren of the Faculty, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to Dr. <hi>Carr</hi> of <hi>Cambridg,</hi> Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> of <hi>York,</hi> Dr. <hi>Neale</hi> of <hi>Leedes,</hi> Dr. <hi>Conſtable,</hi> Dr. <hi>Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tadge,</hi> Dr. <hi>Simpſon.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHat Tragick part ſoever the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maedian acts upon the Stage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Fellow, it is not upon any deſign of <hi>malice,</hi> to the party, but <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment</hi> to the Spectators. The time I took for penning this Reply, was <hi>Chriſtmaſs,</hi> a ſeaſon allowed me for <hi>Revelling;</hi> let none of you miſ-judge it <hi>Reviling,</hi> becauſe, as a Chymiſt, I have but Coho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated all the Spirit of Vinegar and Gall I found in <hi>Dr. Witty</hi>'s Anſwer. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable is the ſaying of a Learned Man, <hi>In ſuch alterations few men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the ſharpneſs of their own words, their edge is towards them, whom they oppoſe; but when a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of the like expreſſions are made unto themſelves, they are ſenſible
<pb facs="tcp:59064:98"/>how they pierce.</hi> Had he levelled his Arrow to the mark, he might have hit the Butt; he ſhot it directly up into the Air (as may be ſeen through his whole Book) and therefore by the un-erring law of Nature, it has fallen upon his own head. If he hath received any mortal wound in this Combate, 'twas made by his own weapon; I appeal to you my Brethren of the Jury, if you do not find <hi>(p. 56.)</hi> that the Diſſector, by the Coroners Inqueſt, is <hi>Felo de Se.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He is injudicious in nothing, ſo much as in the caſe of <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Spaw; I cannot wonder at it, <hi>for a gift doth blind the eyes of the wiſe,</hi> Deut. <hi>16.19.</hi> If it be poſſible to buy Gold too dear, in my ſerious apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, he hath made but an ill purchaſe there. When theſe Irreſiſtable words, <hi>(give account of thy Stewardſhip)</hi> are ſpoken to his heart, he will conſider what I ſay. I honour him for his giſts of Learning, but it is Grace only that can make him, <hi>Palanodiam Cavere,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:59064:98"/>and I ſhall not be out of hopes, to ſee the fruits of it in him. Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> gained as Honourable eſteem amongst wiſe men, for writing his <hi>Retractions,</hi> as he got for all his other Learned Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes. Though <hi>Saturn</hi> be aſcendant in my Horoſcope, let no man think it carries any evil aſpect, <hi>to his practice in Phyſick.</hi> This is a fault I find in him, againſt Chymical Phyſitians; 'twere unpardonable, to be guilty of the ſame my ſelf; the experience he hath gained in Therapeuticks, yea, amongſt a number of the Right Honourables at <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> will ſerve abundantly to reverberate every undue expreſſion againſt this Art, upon the head of him that dares unworthily reflect it.</p>
            <p>I know what the Books of <hi>Galen,</hi> and all his Followers, can inſtruct him in, he is not to learn; yet muſt he be perſwaded alſo, that we have travelled over theſe ſhallow Fords, as well as he; and if we have, after all this eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayed, to launch further into the
<pb facs="tcp:59064:99"/>depths, for Hermetick Phyſick, he is no Friend to Learning, who will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore call us Mountebanks; of the ſame Import is his Super-hyperbole, which he gives of <hi>Galen,</hi> taking it <hi>pro confeſſo;</hi> That <hi>Helmont</hi> hath deluded the generality of enquiring Men, into a Labyrinth of <hi>Myſterious nothings.</hi> I appeal to the Experience, and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of you all, if theſe things be ſo.</p>
            <p>Thus much premiſed, I ſhall now preſent you with <hi>Homers Iliades in a Nutſhel. Dr. Witty (pag. 37.)</hi> ſaith, at my firſt coming to <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough,</hi> I had a Covetous <hi>deſign to carry on, which if it had ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, doubtleſs, we had heard none of this, but that failing me, as the Fox ſaid in the Fable, the Grapes are ſowr; ſo ſaid I,</hi> Scarbrough <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter breeds the Stone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This being believed, well may it ſerve for an anſwer to all that I have writ, or ſhall hereafter write against <hi>Scarbrough Spaw.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59064:99"/>
            <p>Therefore have I mentioned your names, my Brethren, whoſe Faces I did ſee at <hi>Knaisbrough,</hi> upon my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from <hi>Scarbrough;</hi> that the world may judge by this ſurmiſe of his, at what rate he magnifies himſelf; <hi>one</hi> Dr. Witty <hi>is able to ſpoil my deſign of getting, more than all theſe Worthies, Men of renown in their Profeſſion.</hi> If the Diſſector will go upon Stilts of his own making, on purpoſe, that he may appear like <hi>Saul,</hi> higher by head and Shoulders, than his Brethren; who of you can pity him, for that he hath catched a fall? for all his brags, <hi>(p. 119.) That I have not wielded the Club much better, than his former Antagoniſt, or hath any new guard;</hi> I do not find <hi>one tooth in the three Combs broken</hi> by him. If he like to come again into the <hi>Pit,</hi> he ſhall know I am no Crawdon, but <hi>a Cock</hi> of the right kind; mean while, it is but a dirty alledgment of him, that wants an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument,
<pb facs="tcp:59064:100"/>to inſinuate, that I came to <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> to <hi>ſcrape on the Dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hills there.</hi> My Brethren, what is ſharper than a Womans Tongue, when 'tis ſet on fire; I have bidden the brunt thereof, yet <hi>Dr. Witty is afraid,</hi> (pag. <hi>90.)</hi>) <hi>I ſhall ſuffer more from you;</hi> what remedy, but Patience, I ſuppoſe the Diſſector hath as much need of it, as</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Loving Brother <hi>George Tonſtall.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:59064:100" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
